<?xml version="1.0"?>
<stories>
  <story>
    <title>Spontaneous Healing</title>
    <author>Judith K. Williams</author>
    <updated>2005-08-14T10:25:15</updated>
    <body>&lt;dtml-var standard_html_header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was the autumn of 1964.  I was 18 years old and had not been
feeling well for quite some time and I didn't know why.  My mom was
cleaning the pantry as she did every year.  I laid down on the couch
and felt guilty because I wasn't helping.  At that point that I
decided I might feel better if I got up and started moving around.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We washed the shelves, cleaned all the dishes and I was in the
process of putting a large stack of dishes back on the shelf when I
blacked out and blood started pouring out of my mouth.  The next
thing I knew, I was sitting in the bathroom.  My mother and brother
had changed my clothes and I was wondering what was going on.  I
guess my mom was upset because I made a mess out of the pantry again.
They called for an ambulance but it wasn't there yet, so my mother
and brother took me to the emergency room at Christ Community
Hospital on the south side of Chicago.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once in the emergency room, the blood started pouring out of me
again.  I covered a nurse in blood.  I remember feeling very, very
cold.  When they put the blood pressure cuff on my arm, it felt like
they were crushing my arm.  It hurt.  At that point, they started
pumping whole blood into me.  I blacked out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I felt myself get up and leave my body from the center of my forehead
to the center of my chest.  I was whisked away through a dark tunnel.
I saw what appeared to be an opening filled with light and an
gorgeous orchard of trees covered with pink flowers.   It was so
beautiful.  I wanted to go there.  I was amazed because in my earthly
life I didn't even like pink!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I started to go into the orchard, I was pulled to the left and
was instantly engulfed in the most beautiful white light.  I never
felt such complete love, complete understanding, complete compassion
in my life.  I felt like I was just sitting in this light and being
loved.  I don't know how long it lasted.   I really wanted to stay.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At one point while I was next to the light, I had a life review that
took a split second.  Everything was happening at once and it was
over in a flash.  I was told that my life was ok.  It was then that I
realized that I was without a body and I felt frantic for a moment.
I was allowed to look beyond and see what seemed to be the entire
Universe.  It was beautiful and there was a realization that I knew
everything that had ever happened or would ever happen ---I had total
and complete knowledge of everything.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Again I was engulfed in the white light and again I made it known,
through thought transference or telepathy,  that I wanted to stay.
But I was told that I was not finished yet and I had to go back.  At
that moment I found myself back in the emergency room on the table
with a priest standing over me, giving me last rites.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I found out later that my mother and brother had been told that I was
dead.   They had pumped 21 pints of whole blood into me.  When I came
back the bleeding stopped and they couldn't find any reason for it to
have happened.  They had suspected a bleeding ulcer, but they could
find no evidence of it.  I never had a reoccurrence.  They said I
should have felt a lot of pain, but I never felt any pain at all.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I never considered myself an outgoing individual prior to this
experience.  But for years afterward I reached out and joined every
religious organization that I could find, trying to find an answer to
why I needed to come back, what it was that I was supposed to do, and
also to try to find a place where I could recapture some of what I
felt on the other side.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I never mentioned this experience to anyone for many years, because I
was afraid people would think I was crazy.  I'm still not sure why it
happened to me or what I am supposed to do.  Possibly it's just to
let others know that there is something to the "Other Side" and death
is not to be feared.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dtml-var standard_html_footer&gt;</body>
  </story>
  <story>
    <title>My Near Death Experiences</title>
    <author>Trudy Morse</author>
    <updated>2005-08-14T10:25:15</updated>
    <body>&lt;dtml-var standard_html_header&gt;

&lt;table border="0" align="center"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;

&lt;pre class="pretty"&gt;
A NDE, as it is called today,
is a rather frightening ex-
perience, but since I have
been privileged to have
had three in my lifetime,
actually I feel blessed.

&lt;b&gt;The first NDE&lt;/b&gt; was almost
50 years ago, while giving
birth to my son, Michael,
I found myself being twirled
through a dark tunnel, with
a bright light at the end.  I
woke up hysterical, I thought
the baby had died.
I was rather surprised when
the phenomenon was analyzed
many years later, it was I who
was near death, and not the
baby.

As a result of this startling
experience, "Training for Child-
birth" was pioneered in the
Washington, D.C. area with Sue
Patch, sister of Gloria Steinman,
President.  Trudy Morse, Treasurer.
My son, Dr. Melvin Morse,
pediatrician, who writes about
NDE's in children, was the
first baby born, under this new
program, over 40 years ago.

Our program was to train parents
in natural childbirth.  Dr. Dick Reid,
of the UK, was the leader of the
movement in those days.  We were the
first to bring fathers into the delivery
room, exercises for mothers, and
coaching lessons for fathers, to give
support for the mothers.

&lt;b&gt;The second time I had a NDE,&lt;/b&gt;
I saw the pattern of
my whole life before me, and
repented, that before the NDE,
I hadn't been a really good cook.
Saying farewell, I asked Malcolm
to forgive me, before passing out
during an asthma attack.

And from that experience I learned
that it's very good to be ready to
meet your maker and a quick review
of your life is a strong probability!

I am still not a very good cook, but
don't feel guilty, since Malcolm
assured me that was not why he
married me.  The medics had revived
me at home, and I felt at peace that
Malcolm had forgiven me during my last
moments.

From that experience, I learned
that life is so fragile, I would try
to enjoy every moment of life with
an extraordinary husband, Malcolm
Morse, who was my partner for
some 40 years.

At the age of 55, when he was diag-
nosed as having cancer, I insisted
that he retire so that we may have
the last years of his life, roaming
the planet, so that he might have
a last look at every location he was
curious about, had read about in science,
literature, the Bible, politics and
even science fiction.  He remained
alive another 13 years.

A practicing Yoga, he died a Yoga's
death, in peace, in lotus position, and
I stayed over 3 hours, singing and
chanting, for an easy departure of the
soul.  I was at peace that I had helped
fulfill his mission of life.  He examined
anomalous phenomena for some six
months each year, all over the globe.

&lt;b&gt;This last NDE&lt;/b&gt; at the senior age of 81
was an extraordinary revelation.  An
asthma victim almost all of my life,
I was unable to pull out of an asthma
attack at the home of one of my dearest
members of my extended family, GILA.

I had overdosed on medication, which
brought me deeper in the helpless
stage.  911 was called, the ambulance
appeared immediately, the medics
correctly diagnosed the incident as
pulmonary arrest, and were able to
revive me within the six minutes
before brain damage.  It was a quick,
efficient action that made for the
success of the treatment, every one
cool and collected to do what needed
to be done.

Now, what did I learn in the experience
during my twilight years?

The most touching was the miracle
of the assembly of the family.  They
arrived at the hospital shortly after
the ambulance, and were there with
complete support for me.

As important as modern life-supporting
machinery and professional help is, I
needed my dearest and most beloved
family.  Sarah never left my side and I
deeply felt her presence, as well as
Mary's, who never left Sarah.

Later, Dr. Serena Fox appeared.  She
works at the Trauma Center at Columbia
Hospital for Women, spent time with
the doctor on call, Dr. Remy.  He had
heard of her, by reputation, and with
continual telephone calls to my own
family doctor, Dr. Douglas Shumaker,
they were an extraordinary medical team
put together in this extreme emergency.

Needless to say the nurses are God's
gift of angels to care for us.  They told
me later, the incident took them by
complete shock.  The possibility of
brain damage loomed very large in
their minds.

Now what happened to the NDEer:
First, there was a black cage I was trying
to frantically trying to escape, banging
each corner post.  In despair, I finally
gave up:  "Well, if this is Hell, Heaven is
probably boring."  (This is what my son,
Alan, says I reported late Thursday night
of the discharge."

Although that vision appears to have come
first, what I remember vividly, is a white
casket with heavily clad manacled boots
thumping each corner tightly closed.

Perched on the ceiling, was the Raphael
angel, with lovely face cupped into hands,
watching the event, with much wonder,
watching the casket-thumping, admiring
its beautiful painting of stars, crescents,
and other beautiful colorful patterns,
covering the casket, gleaming, glowing
white, like a Rauschenberg painting.

The thumping of each corner finished,
the casket securely closed, the Raphael
angel perched on the ceiling watching
carefully, wondered:

"Well, which would have been better,
Heaven or Hell?"  And with a wry smile:
"Who knows?"

I had finally been restrained from
fighting the staff who were trying to
insert the indo-trachial tube directly into
the mouth, to hook up the lungs with
the support machine, necessary to get the
lungs working again.  Michael, who had
been helping the staff in their struggle, was
severely scratched, which was an agonizing.
moment for him. Everybody involved later
told me they went into complete shock after
this experience .

I was so determined to keep off the
machines!I had always said I would
rather die than be hooked up on a
machine, and I really meant it!

Now that it is all over, I feel truly
blessed again. With such a remarkable
family who by some miracle arrived,
without anybody knowing where to call
them! With such extraordinary extended
family giving further support.  And the
remark of the social worker really
moved me. When I asked her why
she was visiting me, she told me most
of the elderly patients have no one at
home to go to, and she provides volun-
teers and visiting nurses, meals on wheels.

What a wonderful feeling, to have Sarah
there every moment, demanding that I be
taken home at once, rather than the two
week period they suggested and David,
her husband, taking over all the chores of
the four children left at home during Sarah's
24 hour vigilance.

Sarah decided three days in the hospital
was enough. She demanded my release
at once, and armed with the X-rays, she
drove me to her home. Maurie was there
with a broad smile. Michael had already
left work, and was waiting to pick
me up.

Erica had decorated the front doorway:
"Welcome home". Lauren, who had
grown at least 12 inches during the
summer, had to lean over to embrace me.

And Mary was there with a dinner, eaten
outdoors, overlooking her glorious garden
and little pool with the waterfall creating
the sound of running water which I love.

Michael took me shopping for my bagels,
picked up my medicine. And Guy and Sheri
took over from there.  They explained the
medication, assuring me it was very mild
and only a short course. Dr. Shumaker
assured them it would not interfere with
the effective plendil I take for high blood
pressure.

Dr. Shumaker insisted I call him at home
to strongly advise against my trip to Syria
scheduled for the next day. I felt so much
had done for me, I better not let them
down and create new problems, so I can-
celled the trip. My beautiful extended
family member Paula, of Signature Travel,
got to work at once to assure that I get
money back for airfare.

I came away with the realization that
although I say I am ready to die, there's a
whole crew of people, medical and family,
who seemed to think it important that I
live a little longer.  Like the birth of a baby,
the rebirth of an adult requires instant
loving, nurturing for the health of the
new model.

My son, Dr. Melvin Morse, pediatrician,
who has pioneered in NDE with children,
presents, during his lectures, pictures that
children draw about their experience.
Some are pictures of Jesus, pets, teachers,
or parents, whom they have just seen.
They are usually told to return, depending
upon their belief system.

For me there was no such picture. No
persons, no Jesus, no favorite aunt, mother,
or spouse, only at first, a crude black cage
from which I was frantically pounding,
trying to escape.  In some disgust, I just
gave up, thinking: "Oh  well, Heaven would
probably be boring anyway!"

Then appeared a white casket, with
heavy manacled boots pounding each
corner tightly shut.  Beautiful and gleaming
white. Stars, crescents and colored figures
were painted on the lid, in Rauschenberg
style.  Above it all a Raphael angel watched
from the ceiling, finally wondering if
Heaven or Hell would be better!

Who knows?

&lt;b&gt;WHAT DO I MAKE OF ALL OF THIS?&lt;/b&gt;

Our holiest prayer in Judaism is the Shma Yisroel,
Adonoi Elehanu, Adonoi Echod. Hear oh Israel,
The Lord our God, The Lord is one.

The Adonoi is a Hebrew Tetragrammaton,
having four Hebrew Letters, usually transliterated
YHWH or JHVH, that forms a biblical proper
name of God.  Reb Shneyer has told us that
Adonoi means past, present, and future.

I feel a deep sadness that my departed partner,
Malcolm was not witness to this. An internationally
recognized engineer, he was also a Polymath.
Equally as versed in Philosophy, Poetry, Plato,
Plotinus, Literature, Eastern and Western Religions.

In raising our six children, he constantly reminded
me that when the child is born, images of his past,
present, and future are embodied on the brain.

Since I saw no persons, heard no voices, I personally
conclude that it was the high tech machinery, and
the total high level family and medical support
that brought about the return. Maybe, this return
was guided by either the images of the brain
already imprinted at birth:  maybe, God whom Jung
defines as SELF, maybe, just plain GILA.

Death is not Real
But Birth to a
New Life
We go on and on
To higher planes
For eons and aeons
Of Time

The Universe is
Our Home
We explore the
Farthest Recesses
We dwell in the
Finite Mind
Of The All

I die gladly
So I may Know
The Whole Truth
Of Being
At One with
The ALL
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Trudy Morse&lt;br&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;Hermes at the Crossroads&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Hermes Press - 1996
&lt;p&gt;
Written September 9, 2000.&lt;br&gt;
For more information about Trudy, visit her website at:
&lt;a
href="http://www.the-temple.net/trudy/"&gt;http://www.the-temple.net/trudy/&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;dtml-var standard_html_footer&gt;</body>
  </story>
  <story>
    <title>A Native American  NDE and Past Life:  An Interview with RC</title>
    <author>Diane Willis</author>
    <updated>2005-08-14T10:25:15</updated>
    <body>&lt;dtml-var standard_html_header&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
DW:  You said you had a time when you almost died.  Would you describe that experience?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  I was involved in a traffic accident with two other people.  We were on our way to work in San Diego, California, over on Coronado Island, in 1970.  I was lying down in the back seat, trying to get some more rest before we got to our job site.  We came around this corner and a Cadillac pulled out in front of us and there wasn't enough time to hit the brakes or anything.  We were going 35 miles per hour and WHAM, we hit the back of this car and I flew forward, face on, into the back of the passenger seat in front of me and then I fell back down. It apparently was enough of a trauma to begin to impact me but I wasn't aware of it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I got out of the car and a state highway patrolman was standing there.  He said,  "No, no, you've got to lie down. You're really injured."  I couldn't feel anything wrong.  He continued,  "Just sit down here on the curb.  You've got to wait until the ambulance comes."  And we were waiting and then I stood up again and he said, "No, you can 't stand because you're very injured."   I said, "I feel fine."  He said, "No, I'd rather have you sit down."  So on my way to sitting back down again, I guess I collapsed.  The last thing I remember was the officer saying, "Don't get blood on my uniform.  I just had it dry cleaned."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then I blacked out.  It started like a bunch of little squares growing in front of my eyes and I was out for a while, but it felt to me like seconds.  Then there was this feeling like a tingling,  and a real long noise, an audible buzzing noise, which was kind of like the sound a locust makes---when all of a sudden the world opened up and there was this huge immense light everywhere and it wasn't like clouds or anything familiar.  It was just this huge bright awareness.  And I could feel that I was everything and to me it felt like I was there for minutes---just being awe-inspired by looking out and something in my mind was telling me, "You are all this.  You are all this."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was seeing light but it was like being in clouds when I'm flying in airplanes---so I like to do that now.   A bright day, flying through the clouds at 30,000 feet and it's like that.  But you're not in the plane.  You're in the clouds.  And you're not falling.  So it feels like you're being held in outer space.  You know, it just holds you and you become a part of it.  It's like being a giant marshmallow.  It's warm.  It's enclosing.  There's no hunger.  There's no sorrow.  No emotions except pure awareness.   Everything opens---as they say, the third eye.   Everything.  All your senses are ---you are totally in it and it just happens, and it is like,"Wow," and I knew in my mind that everything that I was witnessing or experiencing in my life was me and it felt warm.  I felt very comfortable and I was standing.  I now know I was standing because I could see myself standing and feel myself being in that space and being drawn in and--- "It's not your time, why are you here?  Now it's time to go back."  And I thought, "There must be more."  "No, it's time  to go back."   It was like me, speaking to myself.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don't know.  That's the only thing I can say to put it very simply so people can understand it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I didn't want to come back, but when I woke up, I was lying in an ambulance and the policeman was by me and he said, "I told you.  Now you're awake, but I told you 'Don't pass out.'  Now I have to go home and get my uniform dry cleaned again."  I said "I'm sorry.  I just passed out for a moment."  He said "No.  It was about a half an hour.  You almost died on us."  I said "No.  All I did was hit the back of the seat in this car."  And I noticed I was all bandaged up and I said "What's all this stuff?"   And he said, "Well, there's a huge gash.  Your teeth are here in this cup and you were knocked out, and we think you have some back damage and you might have some broken ribs."  And I said, "No--not possible.  I just passed out for a moment.  I'll find someone to dry clean your uniform for you.  At least I can do that."  He said,  "No.  They're going to take you to the hospital now." ---and they did.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
He said it was 30 minutes.  I thought it was the snap of a finger---just a flash --just an instant--I saw this huge thing.  All I know is that I know what's over there now and I'm very secure in the fact that I don't have to be afraid.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  You're not afraid to die now?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  No.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  Were you afraid before?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  Probably.  I think most people are.  But I know now what I am.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After it was over, I thought my world had ended.  I had split my lip open.  There was significant nerve damage through my upper lip and cheek, so I could no longer play the brass instruments.  After it all healed up and all the stitches were taken out on the inside, I realized that the doctor had put the teeth back the way he thought they should belong and they were all out of order.   So now my embouchure was destroyed.  The musculature was destroyed.  I'm still trying to play the trumpet, because that was my dream, that's my sound.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But I got home and I spent a whole year moping around, trying to get myself back.  And we went to Santa Fe, NM, and I found a man who was walking around at the Indian Market with a basket full of flutes and he was a flutemaker from San Diego by the name of Oliver W. Jones, who is a doctor on genetics.  His hobby was making flutes.   So we talked to him a little bit and we traded some beadwork that we had for the flutes and kind of looked at them and hung them on the wall.  They were nice looking.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And then one day my friend says, "Here, take these things.  Spiders and bugs are living in them.  They're nice.  Why don't you try to play them and see what you can do with them?"   So that started the whole thing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I'm here on a mission.  I'm here on a job to do something, so when I'm through I'll go back and I don't have that fear because as I talk with elders about it they say,
"It sounds like you've gone there and done this---but here's the secret:  You can't choose to go.  You've got to let it come in its own time because you're here for a reason.  There's a purpose in why you're here and you have to understand that before you're allowed to go back.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I had that accident I was told that it's not my time.  And what was intuited to me
was my time will come but first I have to do this.  And all these things are in my mind.  And I can't explain it and there's no real way to explain what it felt like to be there, but it was WONDERFUL.  So I can't wait to die---because I know what the gift is.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What I intuit from that is that I am one of the nerve endings in this huge entity of everything that exists, the cosmos, everything.  I am one of those little nerve endings and I am experiencing for this huge awareness what it means to be me or you or you or you or this or that.  And when we all leave from here we all go back to ourselves and we say,  "That was fun.  This is what I experienced."  And maybe it will say "God, I'm wonderful.  Go do it again."  So like a giant kid you say, "Ok.  What am I going to do this time?"  And that's the only thing I can think of to explain what it means.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It's like reincarnation---it's a different experience the next time.  So you've got to make the most of being here now.  You've got to live in your dream and smile with a shit-eating smile on your face and walk around like you know everything.  We are still children. Learn to love yourself.  That's where it's all at.  And in that way, you'll love your life.  We are all varied and different because our life experiences are not all the same and they're not meant to be.  You're here to become of service to others and that's what it's all about---to become of service to others.
 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Spirit Guides&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But there are certain things that happen now in my life which make me know I'm being guided, because there are two people who come to me in my dreams and they've given me symbols that I use now.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  Do you know who they are?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  No.  They look like two native men to me.  They wear business suits and carry briefcases, but they have braids.  They are younger.  They say:  "Now you're a part of us---but you have to spread this symbol all over the world because you belong to us now."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  What is the symbol?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  It is a circle with four quadrants, but the one they gave me has mountains on it.  And I drew that one too.  It has mountains and an eagle feather in the middle--which really isn't an eagle feather.  It's sort of a dream of change.  But it's a symbol of something... some power or something.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It's done on white paper, with embossing.  And these mountains are supposed to be the space that we all live in and this is the physical plane.  This is the message, the dream.  These are the directions that we are suppose to be aware of.  This is the journey that we're on.  But the dream is always primary.  These blank spaces are also important because it's three-dimensional.  There's a line or trail that comes out and goes away.  That's the path that we're born into and then we leave on.  So those parts you don't see. These are roads of life experience.  It's like a figure eight but it moves so the figure eight is moving too.  So your symbol is always in action one way or another.   The areas in here are for storing information.... physical, spiritual.  That's called ATOKA.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  What does that mean?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  I don't speak Lakota, but a lady said, "This is a word we don't use any more.  Where did you get that word?"  I said, "It just came," and I showed her this symbol and she said, "That's what you're supposed to do."  She said it means something sacred, unexplainable.  "I don't even know what the word means but we used it like 'Wapunkanta'  which means great mystery," and that was the other part of it.  She said "What I do know is that we know that we came from somewhere else and we're on this journey.  It's spiritual , it's physical, it's philosophical.  It's everything at once.  But we've lost the mentality to understand that part.   I don't know where you got this word.  Nobody knows this word except Lokota Holy men."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So I told her about these two young guys that come to me that have long hair and business suits and everything.   And she said:  "Do they look like this?"  And I said , "Yes."  And she described these different people to me and she said "They are like twins, but they are also hero brothers and they're guardians.  They are giving you something.  It's very, very spiritual and sacred and you'll know the rest, but keep all of this stuff because somewhere you're supposed to do something with it."  And that's all I know.
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So I still have the original drawing and the story that came to me in that dream.  And then the subsequent dream when they gave me this one and the story that goes with this.  And the only thing they told me, as they were peeling the paper off the back and sticking it on trash cans and windows, was:  "You're gonna spread this thing all over the world."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I'm supposed to make it physical and then give it to people.  So I'm still in the process of getting that done and  it's been about 12 years now, but the Natives are still here---even when I'm working.  And the symbol is always with me.  I use it all the time.  It's on everything I do.  So they're helping me to get this message across.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  If there's a way to save the world and to bridge the gap between people, it's through....
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:    self-awareness and the awareness that we're all connected physiologically.  It's a very simple concept.  Why people don't get it is beyond me because if I know this, you should know this too.  Why do people fear?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I know the two people that follow me say, "Everything that will come to you is a gift and make sure that you take it.  But when you refuse a gift the first time, it won't come back to you and then you're on your own."  But now I realize what the gift is.  It's anything.  It could be money.  It could be stuff.  But it comes to me, because it's not for me.  It comes to me and then later someone always comes and says "I really need this" and I say "I have this and I don't need it and I want you to have it."  So I've sort of become a go between.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And even what I do musically is that way, too.  It doesn't belong to me.  It moves through me because that's what I'm supposed to be doing .  And when I do that and give it freely to others then it's now theirs.  It's the gift.  And I have no control over it.  I mean.  It takes me, too.  I'll be doing these performances and lectures and suddenly I'll be somewhere else and my mind will be shut, but I'm talking about something I've never done before, and I think, "Where does this come from?  I've never taught this stuff before  and why am I saying it now?"
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Or I'll be talking and then it will change and I'll zero in on someone, and I won't physically look at them but I will suddenly begin speaking about something and then they say,  "That's exactly why I came here."  And I go,   "Oh, I don't know where it came from but apparently it's for you.  So it's yours now."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And I can also tell when there are people there who are going to challenge me and say,  "What you're saying is not true because of this or because of that."  And that's when it goes back to "You've got to begin to understand how we're related and I want to show you something."  And they fight real hard---it seems to me--like it's the other side or it's the balance.  Or maybe it's the dark side that's fighting it.  It's saying "Don't do this."  You want to do it this way because those people are going to take you.  It doesn't matter.  I'm ready.  But before I go I have to make sure that they know what this really is all about.  And I'm going to teach them how to be a human being.  And I don't know.  It takes me.  I've experienced it in concerts, where I feel like I wasn't really there.   The music was going on its own.  It was coming out of my flutes.  I wasn't really there.  It was taking me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  I hear that when I listen to your music.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  I don't know where it comes from.  People say, "Show me how to do that."  I say I don't know.  All I can do is show you how to play the flute.  It comes from you.  It's inside of you already.  You know how to do this.  I'm just showing you how to make the tool work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  It comes through you.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  It does.  You know that's when people see them on stage with me.  They say, "Who are those two guys that were behind you?"  I say I don't know.  I don't know.  What do they look like?  Some times it 's an old man.  Sometimes it's the two young native guys with their business suits.  I said, "Do they have two brown briefcases?  "Well, no, but they had something in their hands."  "I know what it is.  Is it this symbol?"  "...sort of like that.  And they were holding it."  And then they hold it out to the people.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The only way I can explain it is that we're a part of this huge body of knowledge, awareness, wisdom, whatever it might be ---and we're like the nerve-endings of it. And we're experiencing things for this huge awareness and then when we go back we take the knowledge that we've experienced here with us and say:  "This is what we've learned there.  I've learned this for you."  So in the life experience, it is very important to make sure everything you do counts because when you go back, you're going impart all of this experience to yourself.  It's stupid sounding but that's the only way I can explain it.   People say "That's too simple."  No, that's really involved.  That's the simplest way I can explain it.  I am a part of something much larger than anything I can even imagine, and I'm only a feeler---as all of you are.  Some get it.  Some don't.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It's not insignificant but what I was shown or what I became aware of was that even in my own life, even though I feel that it's insignificant, everything that I experience here is very critical for allowing this being to understand the enormity of itself.   And its at that point that I realized that what I do here is very important.  And I shouldn't take a lot of things that I had been doing up until that time very lightly or live my life carelessly, and it also showed me what it meant when I would be allowed to leave from here.  But it wasn't my time.   It was only showing me because I had accidentally tripped on the carpet and come there but I couldn't come through and stay.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I talk to them (the Natives) when I need assurance.  A lot of performances are very difficult and they have a way for me to call them and I'll call them and it just happens.  I don't know.  There's a reason.  We won't know right now.  This is only a part of it.  There's a reason for all of this.  They're showing me as well as you.  So I'm here too for some reason I  don't totally understand.  Why am I here in Canada, because I'm not getting paid that much to do what I'm doing here, but there's a reason, a purpose for my being here at this point in time.  I don't know what it is.  I may know later when something finally comes together.  I don't know.  Who knows?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The physical package is not the end.  You go to this place.  That's what I know.
and there's no pain.  It's a transition that's really neat.  You go and you become All Life again and you realize what you are and then you come back.  That's the only way I can explain it.  That's the only way I know to give it very simply.  Most people say, "That's too easy." NO, it's not.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My name...What I do.. it's just part of the whole spectrum of what we do in the world.  When I started this whole thing, after all of that, the symbol came, two people  came, and then things began happening.   And then I would play but it wasn't just the music.  There was something else taking, pushing me toward the philosophic thing.  But the philosophy wasn't my own.  It was a philosophy that was bringing all of these diverse perspectives down to one thing.  That symbol is related to the whole thing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I even talked to Jim Pepper about it and he said, "I don't know.  Keep doing what you're doing and see what happens." He was another musician.  Kaw Indian,  passed on now.  We talked a whole lot about  survival and survival as a Native in modern culture and being a musician and when I went to this place to work with him,  I took just two flutes and I felt totally underequipped but he was the one who said "No. No.  Don't get your horn.  Just see what you can do with that instrument."  Don't set it aside because there is a reason why you brought them and there's a reason why you want to play them and there's a reason why you want to play them in the context of this music.    So see what happens.  Just keep doing it.  It'll eventually get there and I feel that I'm still trying to get there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I haven't reached the state of Nirvana with it yet.  I'm still learning what it 's teaching me.  And even  for concerts that I do. it just ---I don't feel that I've reached it yet.   But people have come up and remarked on it and how it's moved them and I say, "It's not me."    It just leaves me standing there going, "Where did that come from?"  I don't know. but it feels like I am totally aware of what I am and what I'm doing, but something is speaking for me and my voice comes out.  And even my voice changes at that point---which I've learned to understand now.  It's speaking through me.  I don't know what I'm doing.  All I know is what comes out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  You're speaking from your heart.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  It comes out and it impacts someone.   I don't choose that.  And that's all you can say.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  An interesting thing about what you do, too, is that you tie in with nature and that makes things even more whole.  I think about the times I go places and I hear your music and people are always touched .
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  I don't how that works.  Go somewhere... I don't know how it comes out.  You know, there's a scientist looking at it from the perspective of understanding sound technology.  There isn't anything that is just like any other music except it does something and I don't know how that works.  It does something.  It changes him and I go, "Well, thank you, but it's just for you."  And it could be the same song but it impacts individuals in different ways.  How does that work?  Listening to a rock and roll song that I really like from the 60's brings forth memories of activities to me, but it doesn't impact others.  For me it's there, but for others it's gone.  "Oh yes, we used to listen to that.  It's nothing now."  "Oh yeah, but don't you remember the history of that?"
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  You are a wonderful example of what they call "co-creating with God."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  I suppose.  I don't know.  I just do it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  Keep doing it.  It's wonderful.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:   Well, all I can apply to it is---being of service to others.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Past Life&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
DW:   I understand that you have also been led to discover that your most recent past life was in Germany, as an SS officer.  How did you discover that?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  The first things that occurred were dreams and awarenesses that I was actually involved in a different cultural community than I was born into.  There were awarenesses of where I might have come from or awarenesses of activities that impacted me at a certain point in time.  And those were from when I was younger, a child.  And then as I got older I became more directed about things political, social---almost a whole range that was recurring and trying to remind me of where I had come from or where I had been before and where I needed to be now.  Of course, when you're much younger, much of that understanding isn't there yet.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I had a very significant dream that awakened my awareness to the fact that I used to suppress people.  And I was also a Catholic.  But there was a power that was much greater than I was that was forcing me, and enforcing me to be what I was until I got shot in the head.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:   What kind of dreams did you have as a child?  What are the first things you remember?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  Well, the first ones actually dealt with hearing the sounds of people screaming, crying,  and being sad, and then having dreams of children that I knew at one time, but really didn't know, but they were there...attempting to communicate with me, but I didn't have any understanding of their language or what they were attempting to do in the dreams.  They weren't foreboding.  They were more like: "Come here.  Come here.  We're going to show you something."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  Did they show you something?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  No, because I would wake up about that time---and those would happen infrequently.  And then, I experienced dreams of houses that I'd been in.  One in particular, which is kind of German in nature, because it was connected to a barn which is adjacent to a larger building, and I didn't know what it was all about.  But I'm still looking for that place because I had to draw it on paper so I could find it.  And there is one thing in one of the window sills:  a secret place where I hid something.   And I need to find the house so I can find that piece and then I will connect everything.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  Do you know what town it is in?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  No.  There are real close things in both the United States and in Germany that point towards the direction but I haven't found the exact one yet.  So it's out there somewhere.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  When did you begin to suspect that these were actually related to a previous existence?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  Well, that wasn't until the mid-80's, but it was after doing a lot of reading and working with people who had discussed or talked with us about near-death experiences, the Kubler Ross series, then working with Jethro Klauss (author of &lt;em&gt;Back to Eden&lt;/em&gt;) and other herbalists who spent their time dreaming and of course writings by people like David Chatwin and others who had had these experiences..... and I thought "Well this stuff sounds like things that I'd experienced when I was growing up."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A friend of mine from Flagstaff, AZ, sent me a helmet that he brought home from Germany at the end of WW II and he said, "Here, you can have this old thing."  And I was holding it and looking at it and it was such a neat thing.  It was so heavy.  Black.  Big insignia and stuff on it.  And in the inside it had a leather liner.  It was a beautiful piece of steel work.  And then stuff started happening to me after that.  It was like the focus that allowed me to understand what I was before.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I forced upon people a way to remove them from their culture.  And I forced people not to be who they were.  So what am I now?  I am learning in this life what it means to be a person living in their own homeland with no place to identify with.  I am an American Indian and by God, "You will learn what it means to be invisible." And I'm enjoying it now because I understand now what my responsibility is---to know what it means to be nobody.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But I think the most telling was traveling to Germany one year---to southern Germany---and then having these feelings of being in very familiar territory and knowing that I had been there before---and then being able to negotiate in certain cities that we visited.  "I used to live here at one time.  I KNOW I DID."  So I began to get more seriously involved in trying to find out what my psychic/psychologic---other than physiological---relationship was to all those dreams and things that had occurred to me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And at a point the dreams became clear that I was actually a German at one time. I had become involved in the National Socialist movement in the thirties.  And yes, I grew up with all the people that were in my dreams.  And they were my neighbors and friends that I had known at one time, but then I had become a member of the SS and that's what they were reminding me of---that we are all involved in this common humanity and this is what I had done in my other awareness, my other life.  So it is now very clear why I'm a member of a cultural community that's regarded as fairly invisible in the United States.  And the hardships that naturally come from being scapegoated in that way are the things that I'm now learning about what I have done before.  So I'm back.  I'm learning what it means to be invisible.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  What year was it that you went to Germany and felt that it was someplace you'd been.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  This was the late 70's or early 80's .  I forget exact dates, but we had gone to do concert performances and to visit with friends that I had met in NY years before, to put together a touring schedule that would go through different places and represent an aspect of American Indian culture.  But instead this happened.  So that was more important, I think, than going there to perform and represent native culture.  I have talked to the family's grandmother and she said, "Let me tell you a story."  And she related to me about the time before the thirties, during WW I and afterwards, when she said, "We were once Jewish people and our name was Jewish and we changed it at the end of the war, because we knew there were more problems coming in our homeland--politically--which would impact everyone directly.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This was the Fuchs family.  I had met them in Woodstock, NY.  I had gone there for a music workshop---Karl Berger's Creative Music Studio---and I met them because they were visiting, and I had a talk with them and they said, "Come to Germany.  You'll have fun there.  We'll show you around."

And then I discussed my situation with the Grandmother and with Paul Fuchs himself and he said, "Oh I don't know.  That's a hard one.  Many people come back doing or saying things like that, but the way you're talking about it is very different."  I said, "Yes, I feel like I come from here.  I feel like this is my homeland and this is where I once was , but I was this (a SS officer) and I was involved in that political activity which was happening during WW II and I need to know more about it."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  Did you get anything about your name or when you lived or died?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  I did have it at one time and I'm trying to track down all of that because I had written down my name and the community where I had once lived.   I was talking with a woman who lived in Bad Kissingen and we discussed a little bit about it, but in the middle of it she cut off all communication.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think a telling time was when we spent a day at the Chiem See way down in the south near the Swiss and Italian borders.   We were there just to visit and go out on a tour and picnic,  but we spent the night in a town nearby and this dream came that was very very telling.   I mean it was almost to the letter a real awareness of, "This is who you are and this is why you're where you're at now and you've got to learn this.  Because this is what you did."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I do know that I was shot in the head and I died and they took all the papers I had on me.  That's an awareness I've always had.  And I've always considered that the person I was there was also a person who really loved music and participated in a lot of the seasonal activities that occurred in his own homeland.  So he was closely tied to the musical culture of his own people and then that happened:  the drawing away of self and becoming this ---I don't know if it was an evil person---but I do know that in that entity, I was a very spiritual person.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But we were also fighting that dialog that was being given to us by the third Reich and their motives in the world.  "You don't do that!"  But there was no way for me to physically challenge any of that because it wasn't my place.  We were very stratified as a military culture at that point.  And I even talked with the Fuchs' about that enormous power to be able to force people to change the whole perspective of their lives and become something else--a something which is very, very dangerous.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I see that even now working in this culture, where there are certain movements of either extreme militarism or confrontive cultural perspectives on things where we deal with political stereotypes or stratification of our way against someone else's---trying to get at the word.  I don't like that.   Because I've been there before.  I know what it does and I know what it can create and I know that then you become your own enemy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also realize that's the reason why I am the way I am now:  to learn what it means to be one of those people who are oppressed like I was oppressing others.  So I have to learn that lesson but I'm also doing the other thing, too.  While I'm learning the lesson, I am also giving back, I think.  It's tying itself together and as I get older and older I'm starting to find these awarenesses--you know, it's all linked....I have no real power, but the power that I do have is only in the message that's being given and in that, I'm being guided very carefully.  I'm always being warned not to make it a personal adventure because that's not my providence.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW: When were you born?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  1946
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  That was very soon after the war.  You must have cycled right back.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC: Yes, I feel that I completed a cycle almost immediately---but instead of being in Germany, I came here and I  became involved in the entity that I am now to learn what it means to be politically and socially objectified.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  Have you ever had a past life regression?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  No, I've never have done that.  There was someone who attempted to do that but apparently he wasn't a real hypnotist and it didn't really work in the way that I was hoping it would turn out.   But you know there are things around me that I know about, that occur at certain points in time, in relationships that I develop with other people that sort of point to, "This is what you used to be because you know this stuff and now you're this," but they are teaching mechanisms that I have put on in my life right now.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even what I do with the flute, it's like---why do I say this stuff?  I mean it's not me but it comes out of me.  It's an insistence that I've got to do this.  This is something that I have to do, so I do it---not trying to understand it better---but I have to do this, so I do it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When all of that stuff just started pouring out, I talked to a number of medicine people about it and they said,  "Only thing I can tell you is keep doing what you're doing and see where it leads you.  Write everything down, because somebody, somewhere, will contact you that, 'This is happening to me.' and you've got the key already and they can do it, too."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What I've come to be aware of is that there are no American Indians anywhere who have an answer.  We all do.  But we have to access ourselves.  It's in us.  And all the life experiences that we carry within our being are all based on traveling through time immemorial.  Down through time and all those stories are in us but how do we get them out?  I don't know.  I do know that dreams help.  The way that I organize who I am helps.  What I do creatively helps.  All of this is linked---and it's really amazing.  It's like I'm living in my dream.  I could walk around like some stupid person, giggling and chuckling all the time.  I'm so happy.  But I've learned not to do that, because people will say, "What the hell are you doing?  Wipe the grin off your face."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:   Who would you be now if you'd not had this experience?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  I probably would have continued down the same road I was headed at that time and I probably would have ended up a drug user or an alcoholic---totally outside of myself, entirely externalized.  I probably would have stayed in the military and died an alcoholic, not really understanding myself.  There was a reason for all of it and even now when I mull it over and consider it, it's like I was given a gift.   I was chosen for some reason.  I don't know why.   And that's what I don't understand, but I feel like even now with the two entities that guide me --- it's not my place to begin to understand that, just to do what it is that I was given to do, so it acts through me.  But when it takes me, it takes me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So I listen to what I'm doing too and I'm always amazed at how my thinking tends to go in a certain direction at that point and it takes it that way and then people come later and say, "This is exactly why I needed to be here."  And I say,  "I don't know.  It's not me."  I don't know of any better way to explain this.  All I can say is that the power of life works through me and I have no control over it,  so I'm not the spiritual person, but I'm only a vehicle for whatever it is that we all need.  I don't know.  I don't know.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DW:  How do you see the relationship between the NDE and your creativity?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
RC:  I think a lot of it became very directed.   Before that time, the creativity was more let's say, physically oriented---to make money or whatever.   And even at that time I hadn't really thought about anything that would be of assistance to other people.  I was still thinking primarily of my own self, as an ego bound person.   And then when this happened, something changed and all of a sudden I was directed towards a methodology that I had no real skill for. Then I started making flutes and became very interested in sound and sound technology and even after being released from the military, I became very much aware of how sound affects other people and how certain music will create certain emotional responses and bring them out of people in their own way, and I found that using sound in this manner could  even damage people or hurt them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then the flutes came, and wanting to play these instruments, and then discovering that sound, and then being totally amazed by the sound that I was producing and how it affected other people and even animals.   And I thought, "This thing has power.  And I think I am supposed to do this."
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
&lt;tt&gt;
RC has a degree from the University of Arizona (Tucson) in American Indian Studies and Cultural Anthropology, dealing with spiritual, religious and cultural aspects of American Indian survival into the 21st century.  He now has a remarkable career as a Native American flutist and spiritual teacher.
&lt;/tt&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dtml-var standard_html_footer&gt;</body>
  </story>
  <story>
    <title>Reflections on Some Spiritual Aspects of Life Threatening Illness</title>
    <author>Robert Magrisso, MD</author>
    <updated>2005-08-14T10:25:15</updated>
    <body>&lt;dtml-var standard_html_header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;tt&gt;
The following is a transcript of a lecture presented at MEDICAL GRAND ROUNDS, EVANSTON (IL) NORTHWESTERN HEALTHCARE, DECEMBER 12, 1997
&lt;/tt&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If the Medical Grand Round series is somewhat like a medical journal, presenting a combination of the newest studies in diagnosis and treatment, summaries of the "state of the art" and so on, then this offering today will be a little different.  For one, there won't be any slides.  Today this will be more analogous to those other columns in The Annals of Internal Medicine or JAMA  that go by the name of "On Being a Doctor" and "A Piece of My Mind" .  These columns tend to bring a different point of view into the journal which stimulates thought and reflection on one's own experience as a physician. When I was a resident, I must confess, I never read these columns for I was only interested just in the "facts", the hard stuff.  Lately, though, I often find them compelling.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

                Before I get into the main ideas of this talk, I would like to bring your attention to the handouts which are, in part from the JAMA "A Piece of My Mind" column.  These are copies of a series of articles  by Dr. Roger Bone.  Dr. Bone, as many of you know, was one of the preeminent scientist-physician-teachers of our time, a pulmonologist, intensivist, a researcher in ICU medicine, sepsis, editing and writing prolificly.  My own book shelves are literally lined with the Mosby Yearbook of Medicine series, co-edited by him.  Many of us have heard him give Grand Rounds here.  In June of 1995,  he was diagnosed with renal cell carcinoma, which was diagnosed as metastatic in October of 1995.  He died on June 8, 1997, this year, at the age of 56.  During this time he wrote a number of articles which were reflections on the practice of medicine and  the end of life including a booklet on end of life issues for the American Kidney Society.   These articles are enriched from his point of view of being a patient and inspired by the nearness of his own death.  In a way, they are very analogous to the much more well known recent illness and death in Chicago of Cardinal Bernadin, for  these are reflections of a people coming to grips with death and growing from it.  In one of the JAMA pieces, Dr. Bone writes:

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                "I write this to record my last months of life.  I write it for myself, for my family, and ,  I hope, for those many people in the future who might find comfort in it as they also face death,  Three years ago, this could not have been written---at least not the way it is now.  The reason is simple:  Three years ago, I was not dying.  But, even more than that, I had no idea what dying is all about, although I thought I had a fair understanding of death.  I saw death more times than I can count.  I always thought that death caused the collapse of the dying person inward upon himself.  The dying person appeared to be little more than a shrunken shell lying in a hospital bed.  Physical collapse meant that there was a collapse of the mental and spiritual being as well.


&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
                I know now I could not have been more wrong.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                Death has opened my eyes to  life - literally."

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                &amp;nbsp;I think you will find these articles very moving and they illustrate and express, more eloquently than I, some of the ideas that I want to discuss today, many of these ideas also informed by my own  experience of being a patient.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                Today then, I would like to talk about some spiritual aspects of life threatening illness and the practice of medicine.  Take this as a "work in progress" without definite conclusions.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                Every life threatening illness has both danger and opportunity within it.  We know very well of the danger and are familiar with the fear associated with that danger.  Most of our professional lives has to do with dealing with that danger, trying to properly diagnose, treat and manage it.  Sometimes, though, with some patients,  the "opportunity" part comes up.  When it does, it is always striking, inspiring and gives true meaning to the clich&amp;eacute;s about clouds having silver linings, gold hidden in dark places.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As you may know, the Chinese word for crisis is composed of two pictographs - one for danger and one for opportunity.  It is this latter part of the crisis of life threatening illness about which I want to speak: &amp;nbsp;the opportunity for spiritual growth or spiritual unfolding.  The real dangers and real fears of illness can defeat our souls or they can be a catalyst to the inner chemistry of the unfolding of the soul.  And the soul, even in illness and death, can flourish and triumph..  In fact, I would propose that in the openness that life threatening illness can bring, we may be more open than at most other times in our life to receiving a spiritual teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                However, the subject of this talk is particularly challenging to me because, like so many professionals, I have internalized my own kind of "separation between church and state" , mostly keeping professional life and spiritual life separate.  It is as if there has been within me and within my practice of medicine a boundary that is analogous to the kind of boundary we have had in western civilization for the past few hundred years between science and religion.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

          In a recent issue of Natural History Magazine, the evolutionary biologist and paleontologist Stephen Jay Gould has an article in which he argues that science and religion have eliminated much conflict by mutual recognition  that each has  teaching authority or professional expertise over &amp;nbsp;non-overlapping domains:   the empirical constitution of the universe is the professional expertise of  science while the search for proper ethical values and the search for spiritual meaning is the domain of religion.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

The net of science covers the empirical universe:  what it is made of (fact) and why does it work this way (theory).  The net of religion extends over questions of moral meaning and value and these two [domains] do not overlap...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                To put it more simply, the turf has been divided.  The scientists  have the physical world, the material world and randomness as a basic (and useful) assumption.  Questions of meaning and purpose are not  considered to be scientific.  In science, teleological questions, questions with a "Why" before them, are generally considered inferior questions. &lt;mhtml:mid://00000112/#_ftn2&gt;[2] Religions have the turf of meaning and values.  So if you want to know 'why', don't go to a scientist, go to a clergyman.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                However, Gould goes on to say:

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

...these two [domains] bump right up against each another, interdigitating in wondrously complex ways along their joint border.  Many of our deepest questions call upon aspects of both for different parts of a full answer - and the sorting of legitimate domains can become quite complex and difficult.
&lt;p&gt;


                &amp;nbsp;Medical training and medical practice is mostly applied science.  Whether it is physical, biological science or so called "behavioral science", there is little training or even "official" recognition that human beings are not only physical and psychological beings, but even more so, spiritual beings.  That would be a tough assertion to make on  medical rounds:  it is so vague and unverifiable, unquantifiable and we doctors are nothing if not eminently concrete and practical.  Remember, most of the advances in medicine in this century come from the realm of science, and that has been what has been emphasized in our training.  Think about modern antibiotic, vaccine, not to mention surgeries, organ transplants, kidney dialysis and so on, treatments, which we consider routine, that would have been considered miraculous in any other era in human history.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                When we become ill, or suffer any kind of tragedy or sorrow, though, we often begin to ask in earnest, "why".  Science is very good at answering "how" questions:  how infection with this bacteria or virus led to these symptoms or how high blood pressure and high cholesterol levels led to this coronary plaque and to this MI.  If a person asks "why" to his physician, to one of us, and you listen very carefully to the physician's answer, you will hear disguised "how" answers most of the time.  For the "why" answers you need to go to a clergyman, the chaplain, perhaps,  or to a guru.  But if they are honest with their explanations, they too will leave some open space, a space that correlates with the degree of inscrutability they attribute to God, the degree to which they have been affected by modernism, the degree to which they are comfortable "not knowing."  For "why" questions are questions of meaning and science has little to offer in this regard.  However, with traditional religious "answers" regarding meaning open to question today, we most often need to discover meaning somewhere within us.  Certainly others can help us and the wisdom carried by religions is available to us, but skepticism is also one of the cornerstones of the scientific mind and skepticism  is part of the legacy of our age.   So not only doesn't science give us the "why" answers, it tends to undermine the traditional "why" explanations of religion.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                But we humans need to know why we suffer.  It was Nietzche who said, "He who has a why to live for can suffer any how." And, therefore, much of the spiritual work associated with illness is in this dimension delineated by "why".  It is in the realm of meaning and this realm of meaning is in an orthogonal dimension to the realm described by science.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                So the subject of this talk does make me edgy..  But, it is at this "orthogonal" border where  these two domains "bump right against each other" that I want to take us..
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                Do imagine for a moment that we are at this borderline, this "no man's land" between science and religion, the material and the spiritual, the secular and the sacred for  life threatening illness very quickly brings us into this borderland.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                In one of the articles you have, Dr Bone writes four "observations", which, I would propose, come from his experience in this borderland:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


1.  Good health is often taken for granted; however, it is the most precious commodity one possesses.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
2.  One's spouse, children, family, and friends are the essential ingredients that allow  one to endure an experience such a as a serious unexpected illness.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
3.  When faced with death, one recognizes the importance of God, and one's relationship to God.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
4.  The things that one does throughout one's life that seem so urgent are, most of the time, not so important.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;



                For  myself, this borderland became intensely real one summer afternoon when I found my way into the Emergency Room here at Evanston Hospital with chest pains, flat on my back and very rapidly, went from doctor to patient, and, almost, corpse in the course of about thirty minutes.  All of a sudden, the doctor role dropped away and something much more essential was revealed.  Something we all know, but can easily forget in our professional lives.  It was that before we are doctors and patients, we are all people.  We are all souls.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                Therefore, one of the  major themes that I want to raise for us to think about this morning, is that of boundaries and boundary crossing.  It is not  the boundaries between countries or states that I am addressing,  but the boundaries we often draw between professional life and spiritual life, doctor and patient, illness and health, mind and body, psyche and spirit, even life and death.  I, for one, have lived within fairly strict boundaries, trying to keep things neat and tidy.  It doesn't always work.  I doubt that it works very well for you either.  I am not trying to say that boundaries don't serve a useful purpose:  they do.  If you are a physician, for example, and trying to maintain a reasonable family life, you have to draw boundaries somewhere.  There are important boundaries one often needs to draw in caring or not caring for family members.   So, this is not a challenge to all boundaries.  But, to experience life-threatening illness, either as a patient, a family member, close friend or a professional is potentially to find ourselves crossing boundaries.  It is to find ourselves crossing some boundaries we may have thought impermeable and others which we didn't even know were there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                &amp;nbsp;For better or worse, we are living at a time when boundaries in all areas of life are seeming to be redrawn.  This is certainly true in medicine, psychology and religion.   For the most part, it can be an unsettling experience.  And we resist.  However, just as the boundaries between nations that we "see" on a map disappear when we look at the real thing, like the earth from space, many of the boundaries that we will be speaking of disappear when we look with a larger perspective.   And, encountering a life-threatening illness can give that larger perspective.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                In psychological terms, the close encounter with death makes us vulnerable and potentially more open than we may be at any other time.  Familiar identity is challenged.  One's self-image is no longer fixed.  The ground upon which we stand moves like an earthquake and we can feel to be in a free fall.  We no longer can take things for granted, but out of that chaos can come a new perspective.  For the "taken for granted" is also often another way of being unconscious, another way of living in ignorance of the every day miracle we call "life".

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                A patient dying of AIDS said:

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

"I didn't want this, and I hated this, and I was terrified of this.  But it turns out that this illness has been my greatest gift.  Now every moment is precious to me.  All the people in my life are so precious to me.  My whole life means so much more."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                In Greek mythology, Hermes, the Messenger of God, is the traditional god of boundaries and traffic over them.  He is the guide of souls through this transitional space, for we never travel alone.  Humans have always had guides through the ages, though we may understand them differently in different eras.  Murray Stein, a Jungian analyst in Chicago, in a somewhat different context, says that Hermes "represents a type of consciousness that exists essentially within transitional time and space"  ... and he refers to this condition as "liminality".  Liminality refers to the Latin limen, meaning doorway or threshold.  And it is the image of the door, along with that of boundaries, that I want us to imagine.  In the experience of life threatening illness, we cross thresholds, enter doorways.  We go from the familiar to the unfamiliar, from the known to the unknown.  Not just patients, but doctors and nurses, too.  Sometimes, it is quite literally a different place, like a hospital, but more so it is a different psychological space.  And Hermes accompanies us though I do not mean this literally, but symbolically.  We have deep, though often unconscious programming that is part of our endowment as humans.  Call it the "collective unconscious," as Jung called it, or "archetypal  consciousness" as some of the transpersonal psychologists would call, or "Divine Aid," as religions have called it, but we are not alone.  For some this is concretized in the image of Jesus or Elohim or that of the Divine Mother.  For others, it may Great Spirit or the Prophet.  We are not alone.  It has something to do with faith.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;  Another dying patient said:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


"When you've come to the edge of all the Light you know, and you are about to step off into the Darkness of the Unknown, Faith is knowing one of two things will happen---there will be something solid to stand on or you will be taught how to fly."

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                So illness brings us into a world of doors and boundaries and we are accompanied by some form of the "Messenger of God", in our travels.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                Once again, I need to back off a little in this domain.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                I suppose that it is pretty weird for me as an internist to be talking about illness in this way during Medical Grand Rounds.  For our whole training in medicine is mostly focused on disease processes, diagnosis, and treatment, pathophysiology.  The physician-patient encounter is taught as one in which you get the "history", whose purpose is to ferret out from the symptoms a pattern which is recognizable as a disease, and then do the "physical examination" and order laboratory tests.  It is applied science.  And, of course, we love it.  But, many a patient finds it an unsatisfactory, incomplete experience, for there is a lot more going on in the patient role than just a conglomeration of symptoms.  We all know that, but how do we address it, practically speaking?  To relate only through scientific training seems to me to be limited.  For in the face of life-threatening illness, there is a great hunger for spiritual attention.  It is often a time when we are very open, but it is often unrecognized and unaddressed.  We can just look at the list of best sellers by physicians Deepok Chopra, Bernie Siegel, Andrew Weil, Larry Dossey and Scott Peck, just to name a few, over the past few years to see some  measure of that huge hunger.  We can see it in the rise of alternate medicine, where people spend billions of dollars, most of it "out of pocket", not covered by medical insurance.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                So I think that though it may be weird to be speaking this way as an internist, when I cross any other boundary and see myself as a patient, or as just a human being, it is not.  Indeed, this may be a cutting edge of medicine in the future, a counter movement to the industrialization process now underway called "managed care."  For managed care has helped us cut expenses but it does so by bringing in the same kinds of thinking that have been successful in other businesses and slowly, but surely it moves medicine more and more into the world of mass production and standardization.  This is an impersonal world, and while it may have certain advantages, even in medicine, it is not likely to address spiritual needs.   So, it brings with it a counter movement and this counter movement has spirituality at its core.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                In doing  a medline search for this talk, I came across a fascinating Presidential Valedictory Lecture given to the British Royal College of Psychiatrists in 1993 by Andrew Sims.  Titled "'Psyche' - Spirit as well as Mind?",  he admonishes psychiatry for ignoring the spiritual experience of patients and goes on to say:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


"The great taboo at the start of this century was sex, but it is now the last resort of the burnt out comedian.  The unspeakable in the middle of the century was death, and now teaching about bereavement has even come back into undergraduate medical education.  What is unmentionable  at the end of the century is the personal experience of religious faith.... Yet spiritual concepts are, for many thoughout the world, a perfectly ordinary part of everyday existence."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
                So it is in the spirit of breaking this taboo, in the spirit of crossing boundaries, and in the spirit of sharing that I want to tell you a story of a day when I crossed the line from doctor to patient.  And it certainly seems appropriate to share this experience here.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                The experience, which I would like to share, is that of a heart attack and cardiac arrest which was in August of 1995.   It is an event, a date, that has a "before and after" quality to it, the way all life-threatening experiences have.  A friend who has had stage 3 breast cancer and is surviving after the harrowing treatment that has included a bone marrow transplant, dates her "before and after" to the telephone call in which the surgeon told her biopsy results and prognosis.  Sometimes it is a well-defined moment like that: an abnormal mammogram, a chest  x - ray, blood in the stools, results of a blood test or an MRI scan.  But it could be a pain, the swerve of the automobile, or the smell of smoke.  In Dr. Bones's JAMA piece, "The Taste of Lemonade on a Summer Afternoon", he starts out by describing his first symptom, the passing of blood in his urine on Christmas Day.  Think about how many of these "before and after" events we as physicians participate in?  Think how patients often describe them in a story-like way that can seem to have little relevance to us, as we abstract out the "facts" that we seek in the "history of present illness".  How routine they can become to us, how easily ignored.  How conscious are we of the meaning, the significance to the patient of what we often so casually may say?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                At other times the "before and after"  is not so clearly related to an event but an inner realization.  And though that realization is complex,  it partly a realization that nothing is ever going to be the same again.  It is also the realization:  I am going to die.  It may pass.  The disease is cured, we may forget, deny, repress, whatever words seem appropriate.  But, we are not the same anymore.  From a spiritual point of view, we have been initiated into finiteness---into the human condition.  Before, we knew we were going to die, but death was more of a concept than a reality.  Now we know.  There is a Zen saying that "In the face of real experience, concepts are like snowflakes falling on an open fire."

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                All of this is true not only for the person who is ill, but also for all of those close to him or her.  The effects of a life-threatening illness spread out like waves on water when a stone is thrown in.  The closer we are to someone, the more profoundly we are touched by it and everything said just now applies.  The whole family goes through these experiences: adults, children, even pets.  Co-workers, acquaintances, patients, clients.  The opportunity for the teachings of life-threatening illness to be received, extend to all of us.  We don't necessarily need to experience everything first hand to learn from it.  And we who work here in this hospital are also affected, much more than we may even be aware.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                As I tell this story, I would like to try and tell it in a way that you actually are there.  For, though it is my story, it is actually a story that occurs day in and day out, in this form or a somewhat different one. &amp;nbsp;Therefore, it is a universal story as well.  I am going to try and say it in second person, using "you" instead of "I", though I might switch back and forth a little.  But, the overall intent is for you to try and imagine yourself in this.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                August 20 was a hot Sunday in Chicago.  You were off that weekend, though there were some telephone calls from the emergency room and from patients in the morning.  One was from a patient who was in Wisconsin, a few hours away, and who was having chest pains.  She had been evaluated by your associate in the previous week and he didn't  think it was anything serious but she was having them again and was frightened.  So, after some discussion, you said that it was safe for her to drive back to Evanston and come to the emergency room.  You spoke with the ER about her and another patient, who you had never seen but was the mother of one of your patients, and you agreed to care for her if she needed admission for what turned out to be a fractured pelvis.  You were somewhat  annoyed that all this activity had taken place on a rare day when you were "off" but it is hard for you to answer a telephone and say "no" or "I'm not here."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                I am in a three-person practice of internal medicine and the summers tend to be very busy, for the simple fact that it seems as if one of us is on vacation all the time so that you are covering each other's practice when you are not yourself on vacation.  The preceding week was extremely stressful because of a tragic death of a friend' s son in Cincinnatti.  He was 28 years old and died in the severe heat of an asthma attack.  We had driven to Cincinnatti for the funeral and back in two days.  It was very sad, emotional and physically taxing.  In retrospect, you remember stopping at McDonald's on the way there and back and drinking thick chocolate shakes and eating French fries.  In Cincinnatti, you had a uncharacteristic breakfast of fried eggs, hash browns and bacon or sausage. These are the kind of details you remember later, when you read more recent studies on coronary artery plaque instability.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                Well, on this hot Sunday afternoon, you went to Lake Michigan, which is a few blocks from your home and read the Sunday Tribune and stood in the cool water.  After about an hour you went into the Northwestern athletic center to work out, and though you felt rather washed out, you did a work out, of sorts, on a life cycle, a rowing machine, and using some weights.  In the shower, though, you began to feel very weak and shaky and started sweating profusely.  You began to feel pain in both your forearms.  At this point, you got slowly dressed and walked upstairs to a vending machine to get a cranberry drink, thinking that you were experiencing a hypoglycemic reaction, remembering you had not had lunch.  Your thoughts were very slow.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                You bought the drink, sat down to drink it and the can felt extremely heavy.  You could barely lift it.  A sip didn't do any good.  You started to think that something serious was going on, and even that you should call for help and get to the hospital.  But, you were embarrassed by the thought of causing a big stir here, and also you couldn't really believe that anything that serious could be going on.  You slowly walked out the building into the heat and you needed to sit down in front of it, when you saw one of the medical residents from the hospital coming in to exercise. You thought to call out to her to help  but before you could say anything, she was gone into the building.  It was steaming hot outside and your brain just said, "Get home."  You walked slowly to the car and drove home.  All the while, pains were coming up from your arms into your chest.  You passed Evanston Hospital, going down Central Street, thinking that you should turn in there, but when you passed it, you couldn't even imagine how to turn around and go inside.  So you continued another few blocks to home, where you pulled in the driveway, left your gym bag in the car, walked in, lay down on the bed, and told your older son to call 911, that you were having chest pain.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                The paramedics were there in a few moments and were giving you nitroglycerin and so on. They were calling in to the ER and talking about elevated ST segments.  You can still remember some of your thoughts as you lie there, getting obvious relief from the nitroglycerin tablets under your tongue.  But you were thinking that their field equipment wasn't that accurate and that they were overreading and making it more dramatic than it was.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                Denial?  Did I hear anyone out there think denial?  Who me(?),---who knew every step of the way what was going on, but couldn't really accept it?  At that time I just could not cross the boundary between health and illness, being "normal" and mortally ill.  Part of me just couldn't do it.  Granted, it lasted only 15 to 20 minutes, but denial is denial.  How do we cope with such bad news?  It is hard sometimes to see that everything is changed, and to adapt.  How many older patients have we cared for who needed hospitalization but who, so irrationally, didn't want an ambulance to take them from their home?  A few months ago, I was called to care for a patient in the ICU who was in a coma on a respirator, had gained 80  pounds of fluid in a few weeks in the effort to keep her blood pressure up, had bowel necrosis and raging infections, whose abdominal incision had shown not the slightest granulation one week post op, but whose daughter was still wondering about an infusion of massive doses of vitamin C the day before she finally accepted that her mother was going to die.  My real job in this case was not to try and get this patient better---much more competent physicians and nurses than I had been working on that---but to work with her daughter's denial.  I could now understand a little better her denial, that this (her mother's death) truly was unthinkable.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                But when we let in the "unthinkable" is that not also an expansion of consciousness?  Is that not what spiritual unfolding is all about?  Is this not "growth" of the soul?  Do we not have to expand our sense of acceptance, expand the heart, in order to grow from suffering, in general? (The spiritual heart.  I am not talking about ventricular dilatation!)

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                You remember so vividly your youngest son, 11 years old,  coming in the room---you know, the one who you are having difficult times with.  And he says, "I love you, Dad".  Then you know you must  look pretty bad.  As you were wheeled outside to the ambulance, which seemed so RED in the sun, and driven to the ER, another boundary was crossed.  You had been in this ER literally thousands of times over the past 13 years, but never had you seen it from this angle, flat on your back.  You were now a patient and it is not so easy for a doctor, so used to being in control, to be flat on his back, a patient.  You had a strange feeling, remembering being a baby, wheeled in a carriage.  Perhaps, that was the last time you were wheeled in somewhere, feeling this helpless.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                The first person you remember seeing in the ER was your patient from Wisconsin, who you sent there hours earlier with chest pain.  You had forgotten about her.  She looked at you in total amazement and in a few moments, her husband peeked into your stall to verify that indeed, it was you.  You were no longer the doctor "in control".
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                In the ER, you believed the doctors when they said you indeed did have ST elevations and were having an anterior myocardial infarction.  The nitroglycerin did help and you loved them, looking forward to the next one.  You are asked to rate the pain.  This is one of those  things that helps to understand how things are going.  You are thinking, this is pretty bad, but my kidney stone was worse, so you gave it an "8". You are now getting intravenous lopressor, aspirin and the heparin was getting started.  One of the medical residents, who you knew well from supervising him for two years in clinic, and who is a very funny guy, tells you that he needs to do a rectal exam since they are starting heparin.  You remind him to be sure and check the prostate at the same time.  You shift into humor mode.  Dave, the ER doc  keeps asking you to rate the pain, and you think it got as low as a "4".  Time, though, time was getting very compressed in the intensity of everything.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                In a few moments, you felt a little light-headed, but more than that, you heard a sound that sounded like cicadas.  It was that high-pitched sound they make in the summer.  You asked Dave what that sound was, and he said, with a voice tinged in anxiety and comfort, not to worry, for it was the sound people hear when they run lidocaine in quickly.  Oh, you thought, lidocaine - you must be having an arrhythmia.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                And that was your last earthly thought.  Almost.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                For in the next moment, you were transported to a different world, a different zone.  It is difficult to describe, but it was both dark, black actually, but luminous.  You know it can't be both but it was.  There were three lights or figures that were like stars but were more figures than stars.  It was extraordinarily quiet and peaceful.  It was like every muscle relaxed and every care was removed.  There was a sense of movement, going toward the figures, being carried in that direction.  It is not easy to describe this.  There was no sense of time. It was like waking up out of a sleep, and, like going to sleep when you take a nap in the daytime.  It was very vivid.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                And then, Dave, who is  about 6 feet 4 inches and 220 pounds, is  about six inches from your face, tears in his eyes, very emotional.  He seems to be very excited, yelling, "Bob, we got you back. You were in V-fib!"

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                You remember looking at him, feeling very strange, thinking, is he all right?  Then he said, "Did you see the white light?"  Still feeling very calm and ironic, you said, "No, but I was going up the black tunnel."

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                This all seemed slightly humorous at the time, even if it was a gallows-type humor.  But, isn't that how we cope?   I sure do.  How many Friday afternoons have you signed out to one of your partners, your sides aching from laughing so hard at the sign out---this laughter a healthy substitute for the tears you would shed during the week if you weren't so emotionally controlled.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                You lay there on the ER bed and it strikes you what has just happened, how close you just were to being gone forever and that it could happen any time again.  The beach, the sunny afternoon, your home, your family---all seem so distant, so far away.  A  multitude of feelings from all the various reaches of your being come in.  Conscious, unconscious, autonomic, primordial.  Foremost was this feeling of wanting to live, feeling that it was not your time yet.  You felt "in the middle of things", not ending.  You felt lonely. Would you ever see your wife and children and friends again?  You began to decide what prayer to say, for after 22 years of daily spiritual practice, there were a lot of possibilities.  Then, out of the depths from some unconscious place came, something you had never said before.  It was simply:  "If it be Thy Will, If it be Thy Will."  And with it came a sense not just of surrender, but of sacred submission. A feeling that you had never quite had before---at least like that.  It was a total stripping away of the feeling of having any power or anything; but with it, came surrender and a feeling of peace.  And this came up from some unknown depths, for on the surface was a big component of fear.  Over and over again, silently, you said, "If it be Thy Will."   The difference between life and death at this point felt as slim as flicking a switch on and off.  It was on now, but how long, and who held the switch was beyond me.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;



                From there came the cardiologists and your partners and your spouse and we went into the cardiac cath lab which you saw  from such a different angle. An angiogram diagnosed a totally occluded  left anterior descending artery.  It was amazingly quickly and efficiently done and an angioplasty guide wire was passed and the first balloon inflated.  The pain came back.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                Everyone thought this was great since it indicated viable myocardium.  You asked how long one needed to keep the balloon inflated and learned an update of one of those basic life lessons: "Well, we've learned that the longer we can keep it inflated, the better the results."  "Okay," you thought, "but just give me an idea of how long you're thinking."  "About 20 minutes."  It helps to know how long, but with so much at stake, they could have said three hours and you would have said fine.  You felt total confidence in whatever they said.  When the inflations were over and the pain stopped, an intra-aortic balloon pump was left in the aorta for the next two days.  It was noticeable only if you  paid attention to a kind of blip in the chest---a stronger heart beat.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
                The CCU nurses were like angels.  Not ethereal angels, but kind of livesaving types.  You began to feel things were going to work out.  The angioplasty was successful in opening up the artery and even though there is another 90% lesion in a smaller obtuse marginal vessel, there was a general feeling of relief and of having passed through the worst as night came.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                Later, after a few days, when things were settled, you asked for a book to be brought to the hospital which was Meister Eckhart's sermons. &amp;nbsp;You needed to read the one he had written called "Blessed are the Poor", which is an exegesis on "Blessed are the poor in spirit, for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven."  It said it all.  It was in "having nothing, knowing nothing, wanting nothing and being nothing" that we recognize the extent to which we live by God's grace.  And while this could have been just good luck, or just good medical care, it had a different feeling to it as well---another dimension, orthogonal to the others, and it was that of being blessed by God's grace.  Which, of course, despite our chronic complaining of how bad things are, is there, unrecognized, all the time.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                Which brings us  to the original title of this talk when it was given in St. Louis:  "Dying to Live".  I thought it was kind of a catchy title because it has so many possible meanings.  First, is in the sense when we say in a kind of slang exaggeration, like on a hot day, "I am dying for an ice cream." , meaning "I  really want ice cream" or "I really want to live".   And that is applicable  here:  "I was dying to live" - "We are all dying to live."

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                But,  dying to live also points to something else.  It points to one of  the basic universal, archetypal themes, and that is the theme of resurrection:  out of death, comes new life.  It is the ultimate religious theme, but it is a medical theme as well.  Isn't that what surgery and general anesthesia is all about?  In some sense we "die", become unconscious, and, if all goes well, we are resurrected with a diseased part gone or a new hip.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                But resurrection only comes after something dies.  It comes after we have let go of something.  After we have let go, first, of the way we thought things were supposed to be.  We all have expectations, a kind of model in our minds of how life should go.  My own experience is that much of this is unconscious but we become aware of it when things stop going our way,  when the expectations are not met.  And , we need to let go.  Letting go of what we want, what we thought was going to be, and, instead, accepting what is.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                So much easier to say than to do, and it is not a one-time thing, but a process.  It is something that all health professionals help facilitate all the time, but it is not always a conscious process.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


                If we are, as many religious people would say, "spiritual beings on a human path," having this experience of being human in order to learn what we need, then what we have been given, is what we need.  I know this is a very hard thing to say, and I would never say it like this to someone else.  But, I do try to apply it  to myself and when I have seen others understand their suffering in this way, true resurrections occur---not always the physical resurrection that one would have really wanted, the cure, the remission, the restoration of function---but other  things. We learn to let go of past grudges, forgive others, forgive ourselves, open ourselves, break out of the self - centeredness that has, unknowingly, trapped us and kept us disconnected in a deep sense.  One of my favorite songs, by Leonard Cohen, has the chorus:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


Ring the bells that still can ring

Forget your perfect offering.

There is a crack, a crack in everything.

That's how the light gets in.

That's how the light gets in.



&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                To learn to love better, we need to let go of so much.  The spiritual word for that is renouncement.  Renouncement not as self-denial, but as a way of relating better; letting go of unnecessary baggage.  Symbolically, renouncement is the opening of our grasping hand. [DEMONSTRATE]  Reconciled to being finite, to having a limited lifespan, we connect ever stronger with the great flow that we are a part of.  Call it the universe or God or history or nature. It is everywhere.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                I want to read a section from journal which was written at Thanksgiving, 1995. It elaborates a little more on this theme of renouncement, a theme that is central to the spiritual path I have followed over the past 25 years.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

          "This morning, riding out to Glenbrook Hospital, I did a calculation.  It is 95 days since my heart attack and cardiac arrest.  I see this as a "second life", one I almost did not have.  This part of my life feels like a gift.  It also gives life a "borrowed" quality.  We are all living on "borrowed time", though it is rare to think of it that way.  Mostly we feel ownership of our time, of our lives.  We own them.  This is certainly better than to feel we are living as if someone else owned them.  Too many people - perhaps most - have that experience.  But, neither do we really own our lives either:  we have been created.  The first part of my life was a gift, too, but I never really saw it quite that way.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                The spirit of renouncement is to realize one never truly owns anything.  We are responsible for things, for our actions, thoughts and so on.  We should be stewards, responsible caretakers, for the world's wealth.  But possession is always temporary and this temporariness is  easily mistaken for permanence.  Can I give thanks with my life?  In some very simple, deeper way, I understand (if that is even the right word) renouncement more clearly.  We are born and die naked.  In between, what matters are our connections, relationships with the Whole.  The Whole includes all the parts, what theologians call the Immanent, what we might call "daily life".   The Whole is not something separate from the parts."

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                On the one year anniversary of the heart attack, I worked out at Northwestern, the scene of it all beginning that day.  After my run, for running has become my current discipline (surprise!), I showered in the same shower stall as I when I first experienced the sweating, the weakness and the arm and chest pains.  Who should walk in but Tim, the cardiologist who did the angiogram and angioplasty that day.  I briefly said hello and reminded him of the anniversary, which he acknowledged.  Then, as I looked up at the clock, I saw it was 6 P.M., the exact time of that angioplasty, for I remember that the balloon was inflated for twenty minutes, beginning at 6 P.M. and that during this time all of the pain came back.   I watched the clock from the cath table very carefully.  The coincidence of this meeting in the shower, one year to the minute seemed and seems more than just a random coincidence.  For me, it had the power of somehow proving the very existence of God.  But, as a doctor, a scientist, how can you say such things, except in an ironic voice.  Even now.  It is as if that boundary between science and the spirit once again shows itself.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                Earlier this year, the Chicago Tribune ran a piece by Saul Bellow, the Nobel prize winning author.  In 1993 he suffered a life threatening illness  which was a poisoning of his central nervous system with toxin that he contracted from bad fish in the Caribbean.  He spent a month in the intensive care unit in Boston, with a very long recovery period.  He shared his reflections  at a medical conference in Chicago.  Amongst other things, he said:

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                "In preparing my talk, I rejected at once the temptation to tell a convention of doctors how to conduct themselves with their patients.  A team of doctors at Boston University hospital saved my life two years ago.  Some of them seem to have taken my survival seriously, but I would sooner have them effective than compassionate.  That is, if I were to have a choice...

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                No one can tell doctors what to do. ...  We can't possibly tell human beings, adults, to be caring, compassionate, sensitive; to interact, to enter into intimacies from therapeutic motives, et cetera.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
                No other person can value your life as you do. Nor should you demand or even expect such a valuation from anybody else...."

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                He describes in some detail how his senior neurologist was deeply involved with his recovery. The part that came after survival was no longer the issue.  He says:

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                "The doctor's outlook---or if you prefer, his ideology---is humane, but his training is in science, and science does not see nature as having a soul.  But the neurologist, Dr. X, did have a soul.  He was capable of compassion, although in nature there is no compassion, so he came early in the morning and late at night and on the weekends."

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                And as I work as a physician, I hear those words very clearly.  Compassion is important, but only if it accompanies being effective.  We still need to make the diagnosis, give the best treatment and often, assemble the best team of specialists and sub-specialists to help our patient.  And there are many ways to go about it.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                And so as we end, I think we are back to acknowledging boundaries, even as we acknowledge that we pass through them.  At this point in time, I accept ambivalence and acknowledge that there are no easy answers, at least for me.  For me, death remains the ultimate mystery or potentially the doorway to the ultimate mystery.  But I do know the value  and the truth of renouncement and the joy and necessity of living  life  to its fullest.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

                I want to leave with the following poem which I wrote during the few weeks off after this experience.  It poses a challenge that I still feel, trying to live better in this "second chance" of a life.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="pretty"&gt;



The Loom


Time passes and everything changes,
But nothing changes very much.
Four Ancient Women are weaving the Life-times,
Here.
The Loom is as big as a galaxy,
The threads are invisible to us, but have
Something to do
With Cause and Effect.
Threads, connecting threads between lives
And deaths,
Connections, relationships, synchronicities,
But mostly,
Unseen.
We're too busy to notice, too much to do.
Life is work or else,  sleep or else unconsciousness.
Is there another way?
Can one get a glimmer of the threads now and again and live
In the Weave?



&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;



                Thank you.



&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;tt&gt;
Dr. Robert Magrisso is an internist in practice in Winnetka, Illinois, an Associate Medical Director for the Palliative Care Center of the North Shore, and on the staffs of Evanston Northwestern Healthcare and Northwestern University Medical School.
&lt;/tt&gt;





&lt;dtml-var standard_html_footer&gt;</body>
  </story>
  <story>
    <title>The Gift of Love</title>
    <author>Ruth McCarthy</author>
    <updated>2005-08-14T10:25:15</updated>
    <body>&lt;dtml-var standard_html_header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On April 21, 1995, my husband died after a long, painful illness.  My children and their families  arrived home that day.  The next morning, I had a heart attack and was flown to Rockford by helicopter.  My sons had just lost their father and they weren't sure if they were going to lose their mom, too.   I was under sedation for the next three days after an angioplasty, which caused me to miss my husband's funeral.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After a week, I came home and I did well until June 30, when I felt light-headed and realized my heart rate was up.  I called my doctor's office because they were due to close shortly.  I was told to get to the emergency room right away and have someone drive me.   My son Dan was there so he drove me to the local hospital, five minutes away.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As soon as I got to the emergency room, I was suddenly light-headed again and then unconscious.  The following poem tells what I experienced.  The peace was beyond description.  I knew I was dying, but I wasn't upset about it.  My boys were told that if I had not gotten to the hospital when I did, I would have died within five minutes.   But everything came together to keep me here:  My doctor's office was due to close shortly so I made the call---just in case, the doctor "just happened" to be there, and my son was available to take me quickly to the hospital.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was in cardiac arrest twice but my wonderful doctor would not give up.  She worked on me for two hours and then sent me back to Rockford by helicopter.  I now have an implanted defibrillator in my chest to regulate my heartbeat.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
June 30 has a special meaning because I am alive.   On that same date ten years earlier, my nephew drowned in a boating accident.  One year ago, his sister's body was brought back to the US from Spain where she had suffered a brain hemorrhage.  She had been studying for her Master's degree. I'm not sure why those two young lives were taken and I was saved.   I kept thinking that God had allowed me to live to do something special.  However, so far, this is not the case.  However, I do have eight grandchildren, five of whom I would not have known had I died on that June 30.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I used to be terrified to fly.  Now I don't have any trouble with it at all.  And there were some people that I was afraid to drive with.  Now I no longer have fear to drive with anyone.  Since my experience, I am just no longer afraid to die.   I have come to believe that we are all here as long as we are supposed to be and we don't die until the time is right.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="pretty"&gt;

GIFT OF LIFE

Chest pain
Life leaving the body
Entering into a roaring vacuum
Brilliant colors whirling
Beautiful
Feelings of peace and serenity
WAIT
Sadness at leaving family members
Darkness for a time
Heart shocked by a doctor
Life begins again
WHY
Why does one live while another does not
Possibly to learn
THANKFULNESS
For daughters-in-law who turned five sons into family men
For bright healthy and happy grandchildren
For grand babies yet to be
For the yearly seven cousins reunion
Where memories and love are shared
THANKFULNESS
For another chance to live the rest of my life.


&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;tt&gt;
Ruth McCarthy is a 69 year old mother of five sons and grandmother of eight grandchildren. In 1998, after thirty years of working with the Harvard, IL, Police Dept, she retired from being head 911 dispatcher and head of the Records Division.  She can be contacted at:   rmccarth@mc.net .
&lt;/tt&gt;
&lt;dtml-var standard_html_footer&gt;</body>
  </story>
  <story>
    <title>Donna's Dream:  An After-Death Communication</title>
    <author>Donna N.</author>
    <updated>2005-08-14T10:25:15</updated>
    <body>&lt;dtml-var standard_html_header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last summer I read "Hello From Heaven" after I had an incredible dream regarding my Mom who passed on April 29, 2002.   (Below is the documentation of my dream.)  I was searching for understanding and this book helped me.  I have received many "gifts" and messages that I attribute to my Mom.  I know that Mom is with me in spirit.  As a matter of fact, when ever I get really lonely for her and feel down I hear her voice (in my soul) say to me, "I am still with you honey."  Then peace comes over me and I feel just fine.  Here is my dream:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sunday night, June 16, 2002, midnight. This was a dream that I will never forget.  The following simple words cannot adequately describe what I experienced.  I was in the presence of Mom and we were looking over the most beautiful scenery that I have ever seen.  It was not a familiar setting. This scene appeared more beautiful than our "earthly" settings, almost as if an artist added some incredible special effects to make all the colors, all the life, reach out and touch you.   I remember vibrant colors, varying shades and intensities of greens, blues, lavenders, reds, every color that we know but much more intense, luminescent, iridescent.  The colors glittered, glowed, shimmered in every way imaginably possible.  I could feel the colors as if they were alive in their own way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I remember looking at a tree with branches that swayed with life.  Their movement was similar to that of a Weeping Willow's branches moving with the breeze.  The leaves on the trees were various shades of green, radiant as they sparkled.  Imagine fresh raindrops on leaves with rays of sunlight shining on the drops and together they create a beautiful reflection like that of glistening diamonds and gemstones showing off all their glory.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I felt Mom's presence right beside me on my right side.  I don't remember looking at or seeing her but I remember her communicating with me.  I felt fully embraced in her presence.  We were looking at the beauty of this scene and I was exclaiming, "this is so beautiful, so beautiful, I can't believe this, it is incredible!"  Mom conveyed, to me in ways beyond words, "yes it is so, so beautiful, just beautiful."   We were excited to be sharing in the vision and the senses of this beautiful scenery. Then, I saw Dad.  At about the same time Mom communicated to me, "Oh look there is your Father, oh he is having so much fun!  Look at how happy he is."  She expressed this with incredible love and caring for Dad.  I watched Dad and he was smiling and laughing and enjoying himself.  Dad was sitting with his right arm resting on a table.  He was facing sideways like he was talking to someone but I didn't see anyone else there.  Mom was so happy, joyous that Dad was enjoying himself.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It seemed that Mom was showing me how she could see us, in our earthly settings, from this beautiful spot of hers.  I could feel her love and happiness. This whole time the feelings of love, bliss, happiness, and enjoy life seemed to surround my whole being and overwhelm me.  Then I remember saying, with great enthusiasm, "That's what it is all about. I get it now!"  It was almost as if Mom enlightened me or helped me to understand.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At that moment of understanding I woke up.  As I woke up I was trying to grasp on to the dream, trying to remember "the message/the enlightenment" that Mom conveyed to me right before I woke up, but the details quickly faded away from me.  When I looked at the clock it was midnight.  I still felt the glow of the color, the state of unbelievable love, indescribable happiness, joy, euphoria, and beauty. That feeling lasted a few minutes then faded away.  The dream was filled with powerful unconditional love.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I  believe that Mom wanted me to know that she is still with us in spirit and in a beautiful place that words just can't describe.  She showed me how she can see us from her heavenly place and how absolutely beautiful and loved we are.  Mom and I were so close and I am honored that she wanted to share with me just how great her heaven is and to let me know that she is just fine.  Over and over again I felt the message - Have a good time, be joyous and enjoy life.  Make the most of this wonderful time we have together and most of all celebrate life!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dtml-var standard_html_footer&gt;</body>
  </story>
  <story>
    <title>Near-Death Experiences.... They're a fact</title>
    <author>Julia Mossbridge</author>
    <updated>2005-08-14T10:25:15</updated>
    <body>&lt;dtml-var standard_html_header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Steve Fanning is a history professor who spent two weeks in a coma that left him paralyzed. Once he returned to consciousness, he was miraculously healed and learned to walk, this despite his doctor's prognosis that his walking was neurologically impossible. (Doctors and scientists, like most people, have trouble shifting their worldview -- even when the facts speak loudly!)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
During his coma, Fanning had a near-death experience through which it was revealed that he had to re-arrange his life. He learned he had to get his life in line with what really matters, which he says has something to do with "Trying not to hurt others, regardless of the rationalizations your ego presents to you for why they deserve it." From that point on, Fanning began listening to his conscience, ignoring his ego, and began studying mysticism.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Near-death experiences (ndes) may be a mystical phenomenon, but 21st century science now has enough data to draw the conclusion that the Golden Rule is actually a law of nature. A 2001 study published in the respected medical journal Lancet dispelled one of the most common explanations for ndes by proving that none of the people who experienced them shared any common drug treatments, physiological symptoms, or psychological viewpoints. Despite having so little in common, most people who have had ndes reported similar "life-changing insights, heightened intuition, and disappearance of a fear of death." Some of them can reliably recount events that occurred when they were clinically dead. Many of them say that during their experience, they became aware that to hurt another is to hurt oneself. So there you go: scientific evidence for "Do Unto Others."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is not the only study weighing in on the validity of ndes. There's at least one peer-reviewed journal, The Journal of Near-Death Studies, filled with them. Researchers have documented enough ndes to keep the journal alive for the past 15 years. That shouldn't be surprising, says Diane Willis of the Chicago-area International Association for Near-Death Studies, since more than 23 million people have had ndes in the U.S. alone. That means one of every ten people you meet has been to the "other side," a non-material reality that has now been investigated with rigorous scientific methods.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But there's been a PR problem for these particular scientific findings, according to Dr. Neal Grossman, professor of philosophy at the University of Illinois at Chicago. He says that research on ndes proves that love and connection are the guiding forces of the Universe, but this research is marginalized because the greed-oriented and ego-driven nature of our current culture could not survive if the implications of nde research were taken seriously.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I heard this, I first thought Grossman was being a bit paranoid. After all, many scientists think their field of research is marginalized. It's the whole geeky-kid-gets-made-fun-of-and-can't-get-over-it scientist thing. But when I started to look at what other magazines were saying about the Lancet piece and similar work, I saw Grossman's point.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The March 2003 issue of Scientific American ran a scathing column that actually used the Lancet study to argue that ndes aren't real because they can be triggered by trauma (yeah, death!). But scientists aren't the only ones threatened by nde research; the conservative press is worried as well. The September 2002 issue of The Economist stated that out-of-body experiences, which are often part of ndes, are not real because you can create them by stimulating the brain with electrodes. Funny, this implies that sensations such as fear, anger, the desire for candy, and the smell of roses must not be real, since you can also get these by stimulating the brain with electrodes. I suspect The Economist delights in dismissing such phenomena as bunk. Why? Because to them the results mean that the material world wins; greed and power can rule if love does not.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This brings me back to my conversation with Steve Fanning, the history professor who began to study mysticism after his nde. At the end of our discussion, I began to get a little hopeless about the future of our culture. Sure, people who have been to the "other side" may understand the connection among all life, but what about the other 90 percent of us? Then Fanning reminded me of a hopeful fact: nde isn't necessary. Meditative practice, study with a spiritual mentor, and/or prayer has helped many people arrive at the same understanding that near-death experiencers report. That is, in the words of the mystic St. Francis of Assisi, "Only love honors God."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;tt&gt;
Julia Mossbridge is a Chicago-based writer, cognitive neuroscientist, and author of &lt;i&gt;Unfolding: The Perpetual Science of Your Soul's Work&lt;/i&gt; (www.unfolding.org).This article is reprinted from the May 2003 issue of Conscious Choice magazine.&lt;/tt&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dtml-var standard_html_footer&gt;</body>
  </story>
  <story>
    <title>Through the Moongate</title>
    <author>Robert Moss</author>
    <updated>2005-08-14T10:25:15</updated>
    <body>&lt;dtml-var standard_html_header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

When I was nine years old, I was rushed to hospital in Melbourne, Australia after complaining of a pain in my lower right abdomen. They found that my appendix was about to burst.  The doctors were worried about my ability to survive the operation, since I had just barely survived the latest of many bouts of pneumonia.  "You'd better give up on this one," one of the doctors told my mother. "He's never going to make it."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Under anesthesia on the operating table, I stepped out of my body, decided I did not care to watch the bloody work with the scalpel and flowed through the door &amp;mdash; where the molecular stuff seemed to stretch like toffee before letting my energy body through &amp;mdash; and along the corridor to where my mother sat hunched and weeping, my father's strong arm about her shoulders
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   I flowed to a window, to the brightness outside, to the colors of spring and the laughter of young lovers seated at a sidewalk table, drinking each other's smiles.  I felt the pull of the ocean. I could not see the beach from the hospital window, so I floated through the glass and out onto a ledge where a blackbird squalled at me and shot straight up into the air.  I followed the bird and sailed over the rooftops.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Soaring over the city, I saw a huge moon-round face, its mouth opened wide to form the gateway to Luna Park, a popular amusement park on the water. I swooped down through the moongate &amp;mdash; and plunged into darkness.  I tried to reverse direction, but something sucked me downwards. It was like tumbling down a mineshaft, mile after mile beneath the surface of the earth.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   I fell into a different world.  It was hard to make out anything clearly in the smoke of a huge fire pit.  A giant with skin the color of fine white ash lifted me high above the ground, singing. The people of this world welcomed me. They were tall and elongated and very pale, and did not look like anyone I had seen in my nine years in the surface world. They told me they had dreamed my coming, and raised me as their own. For the greater part of my schooling, I was required to dream &amp;mdash; to dream alone, in an incubation cave, or to dream with others, lying in a cartwheel around the banked ashes of the fire in the council house.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   Years passed. In the highest festival of the year, when the bonfires rose higher than the bird-headed finials of the council house, I was ritually joined to the favorite niece of the shaman-king of this people. As I grew older, my recollection of my life in the surface world faded and flickered out. I became a father and grandfather, a shaman and elder. When my body was played out, the people placed it on a funeral pyre. As the smoke rose from the pyre, I traveled with it, looking for the path among the stars where the fires of the galaxies flow together like milk.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   As I spiraled upward, I was entranced by the beauty of growing things, plunged into the intoxication of green, burst through the earth's crust into a world of hot asphalt and cars and trams - and found myself shooting back into the tormented body of a nine-year-old boy in a Melbourne hospital bed.

 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

From this and other experiences in early childhood, I have known &amp;mdash; for as long as I can remember &amp;mdash; that there are worlds beyond physical reality. Growing up in a military family in a conservative era, I found there were few people in waking life with whom I could safely share experiences of this kind. The first person I met who could confirm and validate my experiences was an Aboriginal boy, raised in a tradition that values dreaming and teaches that the dreamworld is a real world. I met Jacko when I was living with my family in a rough inner suburb of Brisbane. We rode the trams and walked in the bush and told each other our dreams. Jacko confirmed that dreaming is traveling: we routinely get out of our bodies and can travel into the future, or into other dimensions, including realms of the ancestors and spiritual guides. Jacko's uncle, a popular artist, got the ideas for his big paintings &amp;mdash; the ones that were not for the tourists &amp;mdash; by going into the Dreamtime.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
       In my dreams, other guides came to me. One of them was a radiant young Greek who insisted on using the difficult vocabulary of the neo-Platonic philosophers; he taught me that true knowledge comes through anamnesis, "remembering" the knowledge that belonged to us, on the level of soul and spirit, before we entered our current lives. One of my dream visitors was a dashing Royal Air Force pilot from the era of World War II. Another of my dream friends was a large man with white hair who seemed like a benign uncle. During my successive crises of illness, he would turn up to promise me that despite everything, I was going to make it through. He told me, "This may seem strange, but a day will come when people will not only listen to your dreams, they will be eager to hear them." He had an odd request; he wanted me to put salt and pepper on my crumpets when my mother took me to the caf&amp;eacute; in Myer's department store for afternoon tea in the midst of her shopping expeditions. This was noted as just one more of my boyhood oddities.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    My Greek visitor showed me a serpent of living gold, wrapped around a staff, and told me that this sign would heal me. Walking home from school, aged eleven, I saw a stormy sky open to reveal the same image blown up to colossal proportions. After this, my series of life-threatening illnesses ceased.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    As I followed my dreams in adult life, I found that it was possible to journey into multidimensional reality without undergoing the ordeals of my boyhood: that every night, in our dreams, gateways open into realms of limitless adventure and possibility. Many decades later, I returned to Australia from my new home in upstate New York to teach dreamwork techniques to large audiences.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    At an exhibition of Aboriginal art in a Sydney museum, I found myself in front of a wall of paintings that depicted, rather exactly, the beings I had encountered when I went flying through the moon-gate of Luna Park. They were the work of an Arnhem Land artist, who called the pale elongated forms he had painted "mimi spirits". He said that when he gets sick, he goes to live among these spirits; when he gets well, he returns.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   In Melbourne, I went to Myer's department store, to eat crumpets with salt and pepper in the caf&amp;eacute;. I discovered that crumpets are no longer on the menu. But as I glanced at myself in a mirror, I saw the big man with white hair who had visited me in my childhood, and I realized he had kept his promise.



&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;FONT SIZE="-2"&gt;&lt;i&gt;
  Robert Moss is a world-renowned dream explorer, a shamanic counselor, a novelist and a former professor of ancient history. His fascination with the dreamworlds springs from his early childhood in Australia, where he survived a series of near-death experiences. He teaches Active Dreaming &amp;mdash; his pioneer synthesis of dreamwork and shamanism &amp;mdash; all over the world and is the founder of a contemporary Dream School that offers a three-year training for dream teachers. His many publications include Conscious Dreaming, Dreamgates, Dreaming True, the  audio training course Dream Gates and the new video series The Way of the Dreamer.  For more info, visit Robert's web site: &lt;a href="http://www.mossdreams.com"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;www.mossdreams.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;copy; Robert Moss 2003


&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;dtml-var standard_html_footer&gt;</body>
  </story>
  <story>
    <title>Grief Relief:  Visiting the Dead</title>
    <author>Julia Mossbridge</author>
    <updated>2005-08-14T10:25:15</updated>
    <body>&lt;dtml-var standard_html_header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

A friend of mine died when I was in college, and I blamed myself. Josh was not sure he wanted to come to the dance I was deejaying with his sister, but when I flirted a bit during a phone call he decided to make the drive. He never arrived at the dance  he was killed by a truck on the freeway. I had mentally tucked away this episode until I heard of a new technique that uses communication with the deceased as a way to heal unresolved grief.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was pretty sure I didn't have any residual grief about Josh's death. If anything, I felt only guilt about the role I played in it. Nonetheless, I wondered if I could ask Josh's forgiveness for my role in his death. So I called up the doctor who developed this technique, Allen Botkin, who does his work in Lincolnshire, Illinois.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I walked into Dr. Botkin's office, I was a little taken aback. I guess I had imagined some sort of high-tech machine in a darkened room presided over by a lab-coat clad, bearded, and eccentric character. Instead, the first thing I saw was a two-foot long white stick with a blue marker cap on it. Now really, I thought  is this it?! A magic wand for seeing dead people? And Dr. Botkin himself, far from a mad scientist type, looked like he belonged at a softball game, giving tips to kids in an avuncular, arm-around-the- shoulder sort of way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Despite my misgivings, I sat down and listened to his description of "Induced After-Death Communication," which he developed by modifying a biofeedback technique in which the eyes quickly go back and forth. The theory behind this approach is based on the observation that during rapid-eye-movement (REM) sleep, the brain is able to make associations and process information more quickly than during normal waking hours. Imitating REMs in the waking hours is believed to activate the same sort of speedy processing and associative leaps that were previously only attainable during dream states.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Drawing on the decades he spent at the Veteran's Administration treating soldiers with severe grief and trauma, Dr. Botkin explained that each client must be moved from the more superficial emotions  anger, guilt, and shame  into the core sadness that he believes is the root cause of the other emotions. He claimed that using his modified technique (www.induced-adc.com) people can safely move through their sadness and release it. Further, about 70 percent of his clients experience after-death communication (ADC)  reconnecting with the bereaved person in a realistic, joyful, inner vision.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As he described the methodology for me in his frank, no-frills way, every one of my intellectual bells went off to tell me that he was pulling my leg. At the same time, I had a strong gut feeling that said he was onto something. Being a good scientist, I trusted my gut. I let him do a short session with me, even though I told him I had no grief.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One minute later, after simply looking at the moving wand and listening to him gently ask me to get in touch with my grief, I was filled with images of my last fateful interaction with Josh. I watched some more waves of the magic wand and started to cry, seeing images of his death. As my sadness began to wane, I got in touch with a happy memory of Josh. Then I closed my eyes and actually had an ADC.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Simply, without pretense, I saw Josh walk out from behind a door. My friend jumped around with his youthful enthusiasm, beaming at me. I felt great joy at the connection but I couldn't tell whether I was making the whole thing up. He told me I wasn't to blame and I believed him. Then I saw Josh playing with his sister's dog. I didn't know she had one. We said good-bye and I opened my eyes, laughing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The experience seemed too simple, too light. There were no trumpets, no bright tunnels, just a conversation with Josh. Dr. Botkin had mentioned that people are surprised by how "normal" ADC seems; I certainly was. He also mentioned that neither the therapist nor the client has to believe in the validity of ADC for it to heal  grief is resolved through the reconnection, whether real or imagined.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Later I found out that Josh's sister's dog had died, and it was the same breed as the one I had seen in my vision. Yet I still don't know what's real. What I do know is that when I think of Josh, I no longer dwell on the images of me calling him or of his car getting hit. Instead, I see Josh walking toward me, laughing and playing with an angel dog. For now, this is the only kind of proof I need.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;tt&gt;
Julia Mossbridge, a Chicago-based writer, is also a mother, cognitive neuroscientist, and author of Unfolding: The Perpetual Science of Your Soul's Work (New World Library www.unfolding.org).  Reprinted with permission from Conscious Choice magazine, November 2003.
&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dtml-var standard_html_footer&gt;</body>
  </story>
  <story>
    <title>Aftereffects of My Near-Death Experience</title>
    <author>Haneefa Mateen</author>
    <updated>2011-08-05T10:00:42</updated>
    <body>&lt;dtml-var standard_html_header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had a near-death experience on January 4, 1982 after a misdiagnosed
ruptured ectopic pregnancy.  Four days I laid in a hospital bed
before "emergency surgery" was done.  I don't remember much of the
details of the NDE other then looking down from the ceiling at my
body in the hospital bed.  Later, I woke up with the question "What
have I been doing with my life?" repeating again and again in my
head.  The following is an account of the aftereffects of my
near-death experience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;First Seven Years:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Immediately after the near-death experience and for the following
year, I grieved for the loss of my baby.  Yet I also felt almost
blissful.  Perhaps I brought back some of the peace I had experienced
on the other side.  I became more outgoing and less shy.  The
question "What have I been doing with my life?" remained in my head.
I began changing my life accordingly.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I returned to college where I made several friends and acquaintances
which gave me a social life that I did not have before.  In nursing
school, I discovered that I really didn't need to study.  After a
while I was falling asleep whenever I opened a textbook, but I still
excelled on tests.  It was like I "inhaled" the lectures even though
this included subjects with a lot of material such as pharmacology,
microbiology, anatomy and physiology and of course, nursing as it
related to each disease from infancy to old age.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My husband could not deal with the changes in my life or my
blossoming personality--mostly because he was no longer the center of
my attention as I had new other interests.  I still cared for him and
our home but I now had a life too.  Basically he was wasting his life
out in the streets and not home much anyway.  After the near-death
experience, I chose not to enable him anymore.  I used to make sure
he was awake to go to work after he had been out all night.  We had
three alarm clocks in the bedroom set at different times and he still
would not get up unless I poked and yelled at him.  My clinical
rotations were on different shifts the next semester, so I was not
there anyway.  I stopped covering up for him and things went from bad
to worse.  We divorced soon after I graduated.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the seventh year I started to have psychic experiences.  My
mother's spirit visited me for three nights in a row.  She had
disappeared almost 12 years earlier.  I couldn't stand crowds, even
5-7 people, because I felt other people's physical as well as
emotional pain.  One day, I experienced both day and night at the
same time.  In other words, it was daytime but as I walked along
outside, what I saw, felt and experienced was nighttime for a short
while.  While writing, my pen and hand often took off by themselves.
I saw several of my past lives.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Physically, I would get terrible stomach aches that would last two
days whenever I would eat meat.  I developed allergies to gluten,
dairy, cats, mold and medications that didn't bother me before.
Lights, music and violent media became intolerable.  For years I
didn't have a television in my home and rarely turned on the radio.
Watches with batteries stopped  soon after being on my wrist.
Initially I actually blamed my mother-in-law for giving me cheap
gifts.  However, when I purchased my own watches, the same thing
happened.  Eventually, I tired of replacing batteries and stopped
wearing watches.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Seven to Fourteenth Years:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
During the eighth year, the psychic experiences escalated to
unbearable.  I knew about the Gulf War before it was announced in the
media, having seen and felt the terror of the women and children
running down the street from the orange flames for several nights
prior.  Four months after the war ended the US admitted it bombed
civilians.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I knew when the phone and doorbell would ring who would be there.
But I also knew what people were thinking and believe me you don't
want to know when your friends are not telling the truth.  It was
horrible!  So I prayed for God to remove this ability from me.  It
lasted three weeks and then begin to decrease to a more tolerable
level.  Over the years it has become barely perceptible.  I am aware
that it still exists but I can choose when to respond.  I continued
to know about events happening on the other side of the world and the
Oklahoma bombing, mostly in the form of extreme anxiety instead of
visually, hour prior to the news broadcast.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Other unsettling incidences were visual images involving young
children, just minutes before potentially dangerous accidents
happened.  I was dozing on a stalled chartered bus parked on the side
of the highway, waiting for repairs.  I kept seeing a little boy
running out onto the highway.  I got up out of my seat, looking
around I saw a real little boy playing on the grass several feet from
the bus.  I told another woman sitting across the aisle.  She said
the father was watching him so I sat down and closed my eyes.  Again,
I saw the little boy running out onto the highway.  I looked out the
window and he was running out onto the highway.  I leaped off the bus
and onto the highway, grabbing him without any thought for my life.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A similar thing happened soon after this when I was at my sister's
home and I saw an image of my toddling nephew falling down the
stairs.  His mother and my sister were both standing close to him so
I assumed they were watching him.  I was on the other side of the
room.  He fell partially down the carpeted stairs and was okay, but I
wasn't.  I was shook up that the responsibility was on me to save the
children because I saw it and the parents didn't and to keep my mouth
shut so as not to embarrass them (or myself).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some premonitions and events have actually been humorous.  I dreamed
about a friend's pregnancy in another city before she even knew she
was pregnant.  Funny thing--in the dream she was craving chicken so a
mutual friend and I were driving around in the middle of the night
trying to find an open chicken restaurant and we were all vegetarian!
I told her and she denied she was pregnant.  Her daughter is four
years old now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Have you ever forgotten to turn off the stove and come home hours
later to find the food and the pot safe as if time has been put on
hold?  If I'd been at home it would have been hopelessly burnt for
sure!  Just curious if this is common.  This has happened to me
several times.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There have also been several deja vu experiences such as having a
dream or a flash of an image and then several years later being in
the place seen previously even though I'd never been there or even
heard of it.  Some occurred way across the USA or the world!  Often
the dreams were forgotten about as insignificant and then later I
recognized the exact words spoken and the previously unknown people.
It's embarrassing to be staring in awe as the recognition sinks in
with tears streaming down your cheeks in a room full of people.  And
you can't explain that you now know you have made the right decision
to take the risk to get there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One consolation has been an image of a field of flowers, mostly red,
which instantly fills me with an incredible feeling of peace and
relaxation.  It is the only memory of the near-death experience
itself, other than looking down on my body.  Since the NDE I've been
on what seems like a never-ending search for that incredible peace
and unconditional love on earth.  The closest I have come to it was
learning meditation when I see very vividly colored fields of flowers
and feel the peace again.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Fourteenth to Twentieth Years:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These recent years have been quieter in terms of psychic and physical
changes, perhaps because I have integrated them into my life as more
normal.  My allergies and sensitivities to light and noise is less.
The most significant development has been my ability to relate to
people instead of withdrawing from them because I didn't know how to
handle the vivid visual or dream information I would get about them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
However some life changes since 1994 have been unsettling and
challenging.  Some of this time has been wonderful and I have felt
whole and fulfilled better than I ever can remember.  But the years
leading up to this and since then have been rough.  I questioned my
life purpose and direction.  Was I going backwards or forwards?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At PMH Atwater's workshop in September, 2000, she gave us a handout
with the Brain Shift Phases of Integration Most Experiencers Go
Through.  I read Phase Four and gasped.  But the above details from
her book Children of the New Millennium really explains much more and
hits home.  I cried when I read it because it explains so much of
what I have been through.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I attempted suicide last year for the first time.  Prior to this I
had always rationalized myself out of it.  To most people it would
not have looked like suicide.  It just would have looked like
heatstroke because I chose not to open a window or turn a fan on.  I
don't know if it was possible for me to even die that way.  But it is
interesting that I had an abnormal cardiac stress test earlier that
month before the suicide attempt.  I had already given my body a "die
message."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
1999 was hell!  It started January 1999 and ended December 31st.  I
lost my health, had no income, became homeless, lost all my friends,
moved to a foreign side of town.  Then doctors, public aid and other
social agencies refused to help.  I had made major sacrifices with
following my intuition/greater plan and then it seems that I had lost
everything!  In September 1999 I almost died from a simple
unidentified infection.  What a way to have to let go of all the
false roles and identities I had.  Talk about major transition!  It
was either sink or swim.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Reading Children of the New Millennium has been a blessing for me.
Why is it that I usually get explanations after I have already been
through the worst of it?  Imagine how I felt when I read the
following:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
"Somewhere between the twelfth and fourteenth years and, maybe up to
the twentieth, there is another marker--a second birthday--and it
catches most experiencers unaware.  It is a second drop --a second
shift.

The second drop is like a second death, in that it heralds a time of
life reversals and the need to ask some tough questions:  Were the
sacrifices I have made since my experience worth it?  Are my
aftereffects fading?  If the experience can successfully negotiate
the challenges of this second drop, a second shift is possible--a
major advancement toward "the peace that passes all
understanding."....

Of those who attempted suicide after their episode, all of them
(children) did so during Phase Four.  Also, most of those who had
another near-death experience in adulthood had it in Phase Four....

The second drop that occurs is not always as perilous as it was for
the young man just mentioned, but, unlike the 'first birthday', this
is a time of reckoning and reassessment when experiencers make major
decisions that require new commitment.  The first shift can be linked
to the original near-death state.  The second shift is more dependent
on choice, on the experiencer's willingness to surrender to a greater
plan.  Regardless of how integrated and spiritual an experience may
appear to be after the seventh year, all pales by the power unleashed
if the second shift occurs."  (Children of the New Millennium, pp 123
-124)
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;dtml-var standard_html_footer&gt;</body>
  </story>
  <story>
    <title>Life After Death: A Journey Beyond</title>
    <author>Holly Ingram</author>
    <updated>2011-08-05T10:03:05</updated>
    <body>&lt;dtml-var standard_html_header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Many times we as nurses may have pondered
life after death, be it in reference
to our patients or ourselves. The name of
the higher presence may differ, but
most religions are based upon the notion
that our souls go somewhere after
we leave our human forms. I have
participated in codes for patients in the ED
and I've wondered what might be happening
to them as they enter the realm
between life and death. Are near-death
experiences real? Are there second
chances? I wonder no more.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On Aug. 25, 1998, I had spinal surgery to
correct flatback syndrome, a condition
caused by the Harrington rods that were
placed in my spine 20 years ago to
correct scoliosis. The surgery was
scheduled to last about 10 to 12 hours, but
things didn't go as planned. Five hours
into the surgery, something went
wrong. I had been taking large doses of
several arthritis medications and
injectable steroids preoperatively. Most
likely because of these drugs I started
to bleed heavily. To stabilize me the
physicians gave me large amounts of
fluids. When it was all over, I had
received nine liters of normal saline and 15
units of blood, platelets, albumin, and
fresh-frozen plasma. Still my heart rate
was 240 beats per minute and my blood
pressure was only 70 on palpation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My lungs filled with fluid, and I was in
fulminating pulmonary edema. My
physicians had to stop the procedure and
were unsure whether I would survive.
Several hours after the surgery, I awoke
intubated to hear a full description of
what had happened and that I was in
critical condition. Luckily, before I heard
this discussion I had already wiggled my
toes and moved my fingers and had
assured myself I was okay. Listening to
the graphic description was rather
shocking, but I felt fairly well and went
back to sleep. I awoke many times that
night choking on the fluid in my lungs,
in need of suctioning. I noticed the fluid
was blood-tinged, but I was too drugged
to be terribly concerned.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Journey&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The next morning - I know it was morning
because I could see the sunlight
from windows in my room - I was trying to
get my bearings when a strange
feeling came over me. I closed my eyes.
At first I felt a coldness in my legs, then
it slowly moved up my body. Next I felt
no pain. I could no longer feel the
respirator breathing for me. I no longer
felt my three large incisions, nor was I
any longer aware of having my hands tied
to the bed. It was as if none of what
had happened to me existed. All the tubes
and drains, all the machines and
noise were gone. Once the coldness
covered me completely, a feeling of
peace, comfort, and love enveloped me. I
had never felt anything like this
before. There are no words to describe
just how I felt.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then, someone started to talk to me. I
say "He" but there was no gender or
form to the presence. "He" explained what
had gone wrong and just how sick I
was. I had wanted to end my life before
the surgery because of all the pain,
disability, and depression. "He" let me
know that "He" was aware of how hard I
had fought. "He" was satisfied and
assured me I could also be satisfied that I
had tried my best. "He" offered me a
choice and had come to show me what
death was like and that there was nothing
of which to be afraid. The way I was
feeling at that moment would be how I
would feel for eternity. The pain and
suffering would be over. I could rest if
I were to go with him. The feeling was so
wonderful, so peaceful, so calm, so perfect.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Alternatively, I could return to the
world of the living and work my way through the
pain and long recovery. It was made clear
to me that nothing else would go
wrong, if that were my choice. I was
overwhelmed by this wonderful state. There
was no way I was going to turn my back on
it. Yes, I was ready to go! Yes, I had
had enough! Yes, I had fought the best
fight I could and was more than willing
to follow and enjoy this fantastic new
experience. I was instructed to just close
my eyes and follow. Funny, they were
already closed, but I visualized them
closing in my mind.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Just as my lids were coming together the
face of my eight-year old daughter
flashed before me. I had had a brief
thought of my husband earlier but
discounted it immediately. As a grown
man, being left alone would be hard, but
he would be able to survive without me.
My daughter, no! Nor my son! My eyes
flew open in my mind and I started to
scream "NO, NO, NO, I will NOT! I will not
leave my children."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Return&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Do not ask me how I know, but at that
moment I felt a smile. I did not see a face
but I felt the smile and its warmth
radiate through my whole body. I had not
been influenced directly; I had been
allowed to make my own decision, but
something put the image of my daughter
before my eyes. I had become rather
self-centered before the surgery. The
struggle to keep living was my entire
focus and my family had taken a back
seat. The warmth stayed with me for a
short time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then, suddenly, with a jolt, I could hear
and feel all the machines again. The
pain had returned. My hands were tied.
The respirator whooshed. I opened my
eyes and could see the hospital room. The
first real day of my long recovery
had begun. I spent several more days on
the respirator until the fluid cleared
from my lungs. One week after the first
surgery, I returned to the OR and they
finished the surgery. I bled again and
needed six more units of blood, but I
knew I was in no real danger. I was being
watched over the whole time.
Miraculously I went home from the
hospital four days postoperatively to
celebrate my daughter's ninth birthday
the following day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Not Again&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Three weeks postop, while rolling over in
bed, I dislocated two disks in my
neck. I endured the pain for another
three weeks before returning to the
hospital. The pain was terrible and
nothing could control it. They tried morphine
and more than 40 trigger-point
injections. I screamed in my head, "You lied to
me." I was angry and disappointed. I had
not been told the whole truth. I knew
my recovery would be long and hard. I
knew it was going to take all my strength
to accomplish, but I had been led to
believe nothing else would go wrong. Yet
here I was in horrible shape again
looking at cervical fusion surgery. How could
this have happened? I felt so abandoned.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It took time for me to realize that I had
not been abandoned at all. I was being
given a reminder. I had been treated to a
special gift. I had lived through it and
had forced myself to forget about it as
soon as it was over. I had not learned my
lesson. What lesson? The lesson that I
should share my experience and not
be ashamed of it. I should use my gift,
the best I could, to assure others that
death is not really something to be feared.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But I had been embarrassed to talk about
it. I thought it was hokey. Although I
had always wondered if near-death
experiences were real, now that I had had
one, I rejected it. It took even longer
for me to be able to freely talk about it to
others. Once I did, I could see the
comfort in their faces as I described the
sensations and total state of peace, as
the tears streamed down my cheeks.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Yes, I was meant to talk about it, share
it. Many people have told me how much
better it has made them feel to hear my
story. For the dying, it validated their
hopes and beliefs. For their families, it
gave comfort and made their own grief
less, knowing their loved ones were going
someplace - a place full of love
and peace. I assured them that grieving
is for the living, not the dead. We all
miss those we lose. That pain is real,
but those who leave us enjoy a state the
living do not experience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Lessons Learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some people say when one door closes
another opens. Most of the time it's
hard for the person involved to see any
good behind a loss or major change. My
surgery meant I could no longer be an ED
nurse. I now have many restrictions
in my life.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
ED nursing was my life and my soul. It
was who and what I was. The loss was
devastating to me. For a long time I had
no idea what I would do with the rest of
my life. The hardest part of my physical
recovery took one year, though I am still
learning how to adapt my life.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But through it all I have not been alone.
"Chance" led me to a new job as a
clinical researcher working on a national
drug study. I have shared my
experience with nurses, lab technicians,
the hospital chaplain, and some of my
patients' families, when appropriate. I
may not be an ED nurse anymore, but I
am a better, more open and forgiving
person. And that makes me a better
nurse. I found my open door.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Holly Ingram, RN, CEN, works for Fusion
Clinical Trials, Middletown, NJ.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;font size="-1"&gt;
&lt;i&gt;
Reprinted with permission of
Nursing Spectrum magazine.
April 03, 2000
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/font&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dtml-var standard_html_footer&gt;</body>
  </story>
  <story>
    <title>My Story of Spiritual Opening</title>
    <author>Ingrid Dilley</author>
    <updated>2011-08-05T10:04:02</updated>
    <body>&lt;dtml-var standard_html_header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;tt&gt;
Ingrid Dilley, B.S., is a cancer survivor for over 30 years. She is a founder and facilitator/trainer for the Renewing Life program in hospitals across the country, which helps people to make the most of life when dealing with a life-threatening or chronic physical illness.
&lt;/tt&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I was 16 years old, I was operated on
for lumps in both sides of my neck. These were removed, and I was
told I had cancer, but that they thought they got it all. At 18 years
old, I had a series of tumors down the right side of my neck, so my
local surgeon referred me to a well known thoracic surgeon in New
York City. I had radical neck surgery and I kept complaining I
couldn't breathe, but everyone around me assured me it was the
pressure dressing on the wound, and I should go back to sleep.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Following that surgery, at seven o'clock
that night, I lay semiconscious in bed no longer complaining when the
doctor came in to check on me. I had no blood pressure! The doctor
yelled at me to breathe and kept telling me to breathe for each
breath, while he cut me open in bed, hoping to remove the blood clot
on my trachea. He could not reach it, and so I was rushed into
surgery again, but not given any anesthesia due to my critical
condition.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While in the operating room, I found
myself on the ceiling watching them operate on me below and hearing
what they said. I kept thinking, "Why are they so frantic? I'm just
fine," and then I realized I was on the ceiling watching them. I got
scared, and in that same moment found myself in a tunnel, like a
swirling cloud with brilliant glistening lightness. I also had a
guide. I didn't see him, but I felt his presence and heard his voice.
I felt peaceful, accepted, whole. As I walked down this tunnel toward
a brilliant white light, my ears were ringing and scenes from my life
passed before my eyes. These were not big moments or events in my
life, and were certainly not moments I would have picked out as
representative of my life. They were moments of loving another.
Moments of shared intimacy. Moments in which I had touched another in
their deepest heart. Moments of shared unconditional love. Moments in
which it had made a difference that I had been there for another
person. There were only a few of these moments in my 18 years of life.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I neared the end of the tunnel, there
was an archway with people on the other side that were welcoming me.
They were people I knew who were dead: a grandmother, other
grandparents, an uncle, great-grandparents, etc. I recognized them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Again I must mention, that even at all
this I felt no fear. I felt perfectly safe, peaceful, complete,
totally all right. At this threshold, my guide told me that this was
death. This guide also told me it was perfectly all right for me to
choose to go there if I wanted to rest, but I would have to come back
another time in another life and complete the lessons of this life.
In addition, I would have to rediscover these lessons, as they would
be unknown to me in a new lifetime, just as they had been to me in
this lifetime up until now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Or I could choose to go back into this
lifetime, to learn more about my lessons. It was clear to me that my
lessons were to be with others in such a way that it made a
difference. To touch them in their deepest heart, to live within the
hearts of others, to be a reflection in their lives long after my
body died. This was the legacy that I was to leave.  I now had a
choice to stay and be with those on the other side of the archway, or
to come back to further gain an understanding of my lessons for this
lifetime.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I chose to come back, and I began to
become conscious of my body, my breathing, pain, light, voices. I had
no anesthesia, as I said before. The doctor kept asking for my blood
pressure. The nurse said, "It's going Up?!!" with much surprise. I
was told days later that they never expected me to make it. My doctor
told me that my heart never would have taken it had I been older than
18. I have had my spiritual guide ever since. I didn't tell the
doctors I chose to come back, and that's why I made it. In fact, I
didn't tell anyone about this experience for five years, until I
heard someone else talk about a near-death experience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was not until I heard Dr. Stanislov
Grof talk about near-death experiences and the rights of passage,
that I began to share the spiritual part of this experience. He spoke
of research into all kinds of cultures and the similarities of
near-death experiences, and how these experiences were created and
used in Native American, Indian, Oriental, and Christian cultures to
awaken people spiritually. I realized I was not alone in having found
a spiritual guide, and that I was not crazy! I began to share my
experiences and trust my guide. Later, I trained more with Dr. Martin
Rossman and Dr. David Bressler, who taught me to access my inner
physician. Later, I heard of Louise Hays' Mirror Work which I had
been doing on my own for years. Now, Dr. Bernie Siegel speaks about
using guided imagery for healing and spiritual awakening. One need
not go through a near-death experience to learn to access a higher
power. People do it in prayer, meditation, vision quests, guided
imagery, mirror work, and other forms.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my own life I have continued to use my
inner guide for direction and guided imagery for healing. It's nice
to know others have proven it works.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;FONT SIZE="-2"&gt;&lt;I&gt;Story &amp;copy; Copyright 1991 by Ingrid Dilley,
Carol Troestler, and Josiah Dilley. Reprinted with permission. &lt;/I&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dtml-var standard_html_footer&gt;</body>
  </story>
  <story>
    <title>Poems</title>
    <author>William Black</author>
    <updated>2011-08-10T 8:31:01</updated>
    <body>&lt;dtml-var standard_html_header&gt;

&lt;pre class="pretty"&gt;
There is a crux about this flame
Who's toils never cease
It burns, and moves, to its own end
In its restless search for peace
How, even the fire can be so bold
To char the pit that was its womb
Look, the ashes, so soon they're cold
Now issued from its crucible, hard and frail
A blackened bowl, a common grail



- - - - - - - -
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
G d is
a cheap no
deposit no return
plastic
beverage
container guzzled dry by
crazed
desperate
thirsty men
stumbling
in the desert happy
to drink
anything
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;


- - - - - - - -

Have you looked through tainted glass?
Past painted pains like those at Mass?
Beyond the wall, behind the art?
Far past the skies, where no-where,&amp;Auml;&amp;ocirc;s
start?
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
Have you grasped the blinding light,
Then gone beyond what's just in sight?
And through the red, the blue, the green,
Know what The Artist must have seen?
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
Do you feel the notes of time,
and hear the silent in this rhyme?
Like a child's dream of what must be,
All secrets G d denied to me...
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
Have you cried out quiet prayers,
And know not certain no one hears?
Woke sound asleep to face your mask!
The question sought, your answer asked.
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
- - - - - - - - - -



forgiveness
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
the prison guard unlocks the jail door
lets all the convicts go
steps in the cell
locks the gate
breaks the key
and is free
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
its a tao poem
it means nothing
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
don't write it down
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
- - - - - - - - - -
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
how many rain drops keep live the sea
that sponge dry the thirst in all things but me
whil'st dark oceans roll over, reaching so high
as waves of white caps anger the sky
salt and then tears are thrown at my face
while fighting deep shadows I also must chase
across lines around circles in shapes without pause
then stopping then starting for no reason no cause
i listen to for the other while silently crying
my songs are forgotten with no one to sing
with no one to sing
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;

- - - - - - - - - -
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
Thy body - so far away
oh, Lord
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
when night is clear
clouds part
I look
your stars
see my eyes
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
when I am in your garden
I hold a clump of dirt
I smell life
smell my skin
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
when I pause the moment
feel your wind on my face
sun on my shoulder
feel my touch
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
when your body yearns
at once filled and emptied
your tides surge
desire wakes
remember me
keep me
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
wait the time
we share our bed
Thou will hear
on my breath

oh, Lord


- - - - - - - -


Writing haiku on the EL
While in The Loop
I nearly missed my stop!

- - - - - - - -
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;dtml-var standard_html_footer&gt;</body>
  </story>
  <story>
    <title>Dead Reckoning:  Scientists Weigh the Scientific and Spiritual Facets of NDEs</title>
    <author>Mark Sauer</author>
    <updated>2011-08-10T 8:51:48</updated>
    <body>&lt;dtml-var standard_html_header&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Deb Foster died in a La Jolla hospital, she found herself on a
stairway surrounded by cats and dogs and mesmerized by a celestial blue
sky, the likes of which she had never seen on earth.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Mary Clare Schlesinger hovered above her bed in the intensive-care unit,
watching her husband and daughter react in shock and fathomless grief at
the thought of her passing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Beverly Brodsky said she went on a spectacular journey through a tunnel of
intense light, a magic ride with angels and a shapeless God to a place of
perfect knowledge, wisdom, truth and justice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All three said the journeys on which they embarked while "clinically dead,"
a period of a few moments when their hearts stopped, transformed their
lives and left them with no fear of death.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They are not alone.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Many patients -- a notable study says nearly one in five -- who are revived
following cardiac arrest report memories of their brief time at death's
door.  They undergo a lucid, often indelible experience, even though they
were unconscious with flat brain scans during the moments in which their
hearts were still.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The near-death experiences, or NDEs, described by the three San Diego
patients contain many of these typically reported elements:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
An out-of-body experience; acute awareness; moving through a void or tunnel
toward bright light; meeting deceased relatives; a life review; feelings of
intense joy, profound peace -- a feeling so blissful they longed to remain;
and seeing a point of no return.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Increased survival rates from faster responses to cardiac-arrest calls,
extensive CPR training, development of portable defibrillators and other
improved methods of resuscitation mean more and more people could be
expected to have near-death experiences.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Though it may sound like the stuff of supermarket tabloids or the latest
New Age religion, NDEs are attracting the attention of distinguished
practitioners who study both the body and mind.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"Some may say this is the brain's survival mechanism, that there is a
physical explanation," said Dr. Vivian Ellis, an obstetrician at Scripps
Memorial Hospital who resuscitated Deb Foster after assisting with her
Caesarean section.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"But I think there is definitely a spiritual aspect to this," said Ellis.
She has practiced obstetrics at Scripps for 15 years and said she has had
several patients who reported NDEs to her.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"Whatever happens, it is more than science.  This raises fascinating
questions about human consciousness, and about light and time."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yet many physicians remain skeptical about near-death reports.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Dr. Robert Sarnoff, a pulmonologist who revived Mary Clare Schlesinger at
La Jolla's Green Hospital in February 2001, said that in 25 years of taking
care of gravely ill patients, she was the only one who has reported an NDE.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"It is not a big topic on my radar screen," Sarnoff said.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Other San Diego cardiologists and trauma specialists declined to even
discuss the subject.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Dr. Pim van Lommel said he often encounters this response from colleagues.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
He is a cardiologist in the Netherlands who led a 13-year study of the NDE
phenomena.  The results were published in 2001 in the respected British
medical journal Lancet.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"NDE is not a rare phenomenon," said van Lommel in an e-mail interview.  Yet
NDEs are, to many physicians, "an inexplicable phenomenon and hence an
ignored result of survival in a critical medical situation."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"Physicians must be open and must take the time to listen to patients
without prejudice."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
A most serene place
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After her baby was delivered by Caesarean section on Dec. 11, 2002, Deb
Foster was wheeled into a recovery room.  As attendants moved her from
gurney to bed, something awful happened.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
She suffered an amniotic-fluid embolism, a rare obstetric emergency in
which amniotic fluid entered her bloodstream, passed into her lungs and
caused cardiac arrest.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For more than three minutes, the then-42-year-old, who already had a
toddler at home, was clinically dead.  Though unconscious, Foster says she
had the most clear and profound experience of her life:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"I left that room and went to a staircase that was going up into the sky.
It was so high, up past the clouds.  I am afraid of heights, but I had no
fear, even though there were no railings," she said.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"I could look off to the distance and see beautiful rolling hills.  The sky
was the most unimaginable color of blue that doesn't exist in this life."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Foster started crying as she described this beauty.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"There is simply peace.  No chaos.  No pain; the most serene place you can
imagine, a perfect moment in time."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Foster said she believed in God but questioned her faith and was uncertain
about an afterlife before this experience.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"Now there is no question in my mind; there is a God, there is a heaven."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
Scientific analysis
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Van Lommel noted that the effects of NDEs "on patients seem similar
worldwide, across all cultures."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
He said he became interested after reading the book "Return From Tomorrow"
by George Ritchie, an Army private who in 1943 was revived after "dying"
from a bout of pneumonia.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"I started to ask patients who had survived a cardiac arrest if they could
remember something" from when they were unconscious, van Lommel said.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That led to a study of cardiac patients who had lapsed into unconsciousness
because of anoxia (deficiency of oxygen) at 10 Dutch hospitals between 1988
and 1992.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The patients ranged in age from 26 to 92; 75 percent were men.  Most were
interviewed within five days of being clinically dead.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of 344 patients, 62 -- or 18 percent -- remembered something of the time
they were dead, van Lommel said.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Two-thirds of those (41 patients) had a "core," or extremely vivid, NDE
while the other 21 were determined to have had a superficial NDE, he said.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Dr. Ellis of Scripps said the fact that most resuscitated patients do not
report NDEs may be likened to the fact that some people vividly remember
dreams while others have no memory of them at all.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Surviving patients in van Lommel's study who reported NDEs were interviewed
again at two- and eight-year intervals, and compared with a control group
of patients who did not have the experience.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Researchers were struck, van Lommel said, by how the NDE patients had been
transformed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nearly all had no fear of death, believed in an afterlife, and strongly
believed that what was truly important in life was "love and compassion for
oneself, for others and for nature."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"What might distinguish the small percentage of patients who report an NDE
from those who do not?" van Lommel asked.  Neither the duration of the
cardiac arrest, or unconsciousness, or differing resuscitation techniques
had any effect on the frequency of NDE.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"Neither could we find any relationship between the frequency of NDE and
any administered drugs, fear of death before the arrest, fore-knowledge of
NDE, religion nor education."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Researchers ranging from those with scientific degrees to devotees of the
paranormal to practitioners of New Age religions agree that the phenomenon
of near-death experiences raises more questions than can currently be
answered.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One is: If NDE is physiologically based, why doesn't every patient who
recovers from cardiac arrest/coma report them?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another is, if patients whose hearts and brain activity have stopped
remember vivid experiences, what does that say about the origin of the
conscious mind?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One thing is certain, van Lommel said: "The NDE is transformational,
causing profound changes of life and insight and loss of the fear of
death."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
A perfect light
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

In 1970, when Beverly Brodsky was 20 and living in Venice, Calif., the
motorcycle she was riding on was hit by a car driven by a drunk.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Brodsky, who is married with a grown daughter and is retired after 28 years
as a federal employee, said she suffered severe head injuries and
lacerations to her face.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"They released me from the hospital with no pain medication.  I was in
agony."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Though raised in a Jewish family, Brodsky said she was an agnostic at the
time.  As she lay in bed, Brodsky said, she feared she would pass out from
the pain.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"I wanted to die.  I remember praying: 'God, if you are there, take me.'
With that prayer, I was lifted up out of my body.  I had these terrible head
injuries and pain, and I had been legally blind before.  But suddenly my
eyesight was perfect.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"On the ceiling was an angel in flowing white robes that glowed from
within, like a lantern.  I believe I was clinically dead at that point.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"He took my hand, and we flew out the window.  I had no fear.  We were over
the ocean, and above us was this dark area.  At the end of it was a pinpoint
of light, brighter than anything I had ever seen.  It was like a tunnel, and
we went into the tunnel.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"It was a light that contained all things; everything that ever was or will
be was in this light.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"There were no words, no form, no face, no structure.  All communication
happened telepathically.  I thought, well this isn't the guy on the Sistine
Chapel ceiling, but this must be God."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Brodsky has three shelves of books about NDE in her Chula Vista home.  She
moderates a monthly meeting for those who have had such experiences and is
active in national NDE groups.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"I have never come to doubt my experience," she said.  "I see it as a great
gift from God. I'm honored I was allowed to remember."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
Glimpse of afterlife
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Long relegated to the realm of the paranormal, NDE burst on the scene 30
years ago when Raymond Moody, an East Coast psychiatrist, published "Life
After Life," examining reports of near-death experiences -- a term Moody
coined.  It sold 10 million copies worldwide.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Other books and articles and studies followed, including several by Kenneth
Ring, now professor emeritus of psychology at the University of Connecticut
and co-founder of the International Association for Near-Death Studies
(IANDS).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ring studied thousands of NDE reports, including some by blind patients.  He
concluded that religious orientation was not a factor.  An atheist was as
likely to have one as someone devoutly religious, according to Ring, who
retired from the NDE field in the late 1990s.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Regardless of their backgrounds, most patients were convinced they were in
the presence of some supreme being and loving power, and had glimpsed a
life yet to come.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ring, who concluded NDEs do not have the rambling, disconnected nature of
hallucination, said patients who reported them came away with strong
feelings of self-acceptance, a great concern for others and more
appreciative of life -- more loving and more spiritual.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
The power of love
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Mary Clare Schlesinger is among the apparent minority who do not see
religious overtones in her near-death experience.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"I had an out-of-body experience.  But I see it as part of life, not a
religious experience," said the 56-year-old Escondido woman.  She suffered
respiratory failure four years ago from complications due to post-polio
syndrome and a severe virus.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Schlesinger said she was placed on life support in the intensive-care unit
and realized she was dying.  "Time suddenly became very important.  I could
slow it down or speed it up," she said.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"Time slowed down, enabling me to go through all of my life and consciously
forgive everyone who had ever hurt me.  Then it was easy to let go."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Schlesinger, who was raised Roman Catholic, said that from her perch in the
hospital room, she looked down and clearly saw herself in bed and her
husband and daughter at her bedside.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"I saw Dr. Sarnoff come into the room, and I knew I had a chance; I knew he
could bring me back.  I saw Steve and Rebecca, saw how shaken my daughter
was, and I decided to come back.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"It was not as if I were weighing a choice, though.  As soon as I saw
Rebecca and Steve's faces, all the energy and strength available went into
coming back.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"I had incredible peace and acceptance. ... It is a different kind of
energy, strength and power.  Survival was more about love.  The love I have
for life and the people I love and the love they have for me is very
powerful."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When she had recovered and returned home, Schlesinger wrote a poem about
her experience, which concludes: "... my heart and soul into one/a union of
love becomes ME."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
Skeptics weigh in
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
NDEs can be explained by neurochemistry and are the result of brain states
that occur due to a dying, demented or drugged brain, notes Robert Todd
Carroll in "The Skeptics Dictionary."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Carroll cites British researcher Susan Blackmore's conclusion that the
feelings of extreme peacefulness -- almost universal among NDE reports --
are the result of endorphins released due to the extreme stress of the
situation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"There are two basic hypotheses," said Paul Kurtz in an interview.  He is a
retired philosophy professor, well-known secular humanist and founder of
the Committee for the Scientific Investigation of Claims of the Paranormal,
one of the nation's largest skeptics' groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

"One, something leaves the body, the spirit or soul, goes to another realm,
returns and reports.  Two, this is a physiological process that alters
consciousness, triggers bright lights, tunnel vision, out-of-body
experiences and the like.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"That latter makes much more sense to me."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Van Lommel concedes that "neurophysiological processes must play some part
in NDE."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Similar experiences can be induced through electrical stimulation in
patients with epilepsy, he noted, and are seen with "cerebral hypoxia, as
in rapid acceleration during training of fighter pilots."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"Also, NDE-like experiences have been reported after the use of drugs like
ketamine, LSD or (psilocybin) mushrooms."  But the perception of light,
sound flashes and recollections with drug use are more fragmented and far
less panoramic than that of an NDE, he said.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most compelling to van Lommel and many other NDE researchers is what the
experience suggests about one of the great medical mysteries -- the nature
of human consciousness.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"Traditionally, it has been argued that thoughts or consciousness are
produced by large groups of neurons or neuronal networks," van Lommel said.
"How could a clear consciousness outside one's body be experienced at the
moment the brain no longer functions during a period of clinical death?"
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The suggestion made by van Lommel and other NDE researchers is that the
mind may not entirely be the product of matter.  And "at the time of
physical death, consciousness will continue to be experienced in another
dimension."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Van Lommel said he likes to compare our brains with computers: "The
Internet is not produced by the computer, but received by it.  And in the
same way, our brain functions as a receiver, not as a producer, of
consciousness."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are still more questions than answers, he acknowledged.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"We finally should consider the possibility that death, like birth, may
well be a mere passing from one state of consciousness to another."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Mark Sauer is a Staff Writer for the San Diego Union-Tribune.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;tt&gt;  This story appeared in the San Diego Union-Tribune on Sunday, May 1, 2005, Lifestyle Section, page E-1, in Editions 1,2,3.
Reprinted with permission.&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</body>
  </story>
  <story>
    <title>God, Lightning &amp; Healing Hands</title>
    <author>Tiffany Snow</author>
    <updated>2011-08-10T 9:08:27</updated>
    <body>&lt;dtml-var standard_html_header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

&lt;i&gt;
"Stars!" I shouted through the thunder to the appaloosa pacing behind the chain link fence. "Stars! You are always the one getting into trouble! In the middle of a storm trying to find fresh grass!" As I let the chain of the tractor shed down with one hand, I steadied myself against a wooden structure pole with the other. The horse bolted up the pasture, as the finger of God bolted down. That stormy day on my horse ranch in Tennessee, standing in the pouring rain with my arms outstretched, I was struck dead by a bolt of lightning&amp;hellip;
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not everyone needs to be struck by lightning, or have a miracle happen, to understand God's will for his life. But, that is the method that God used to fix up one of his most broken kids: me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was summertime in the South. A time of good green pasture for the horses, ripe tomatoes on the vine, and long drives in the country. Life seemed wonderfully slow for me that gracious summer; as slow as the drone of the honeybees in the apple trees, as slow as the preparations for the upcoming county fair.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For the first time in many years, all four of my children had come together for vacation time, and I knew that it would probably be the last tick of the clock before their lives would get too busy to experience this again. I was making every opportunity to show them a full and adventurous summer. Life had never been so materially good! I was thankful to share the riches of my new life as a new wife. We would swim in the pool, watch movies and ride the go-cart. We would drive the jaguar in the country and go camping and have picnics. We would ride the horses.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I could overlook the growing detachment of my husband and the late night phone calls. I could also ignore the mysterious apathy and disdain my oldest daughter had for me. I could overlook the bill collectors' constant threats and the new expensive toys being brought home that we couldn't afford. I thought I could make it through anything - hadn't I just survived my fourth encounter with possible death? Even the doctors were amazed. The venomous spider bite had tried to shut down my breathing and my heart, but the doctors knew what drugs to pump through me and I had made it through - and this had happened just the previous week!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My husband and I had been married only a year and a half. The marriage counseling would work. He would stop comparing me unfavorably to his "special friend" of seventeen years, telling me about her just two weeks ago; and for me to "just deal with it." He would stop needing her. He would remember he loved only me. I hoped time would blow away the ominous gray clouds gathering in my personal life. I kept telling myself time would help, and I would adjust again, somehow.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I hoped that if I closed my eyes and wished hard enough, everything bad would just disappear. Hadn't I gone through this enough times? Why did this keep repeating itself? Why did I continue to make bad choices about the mate in my life? One thing I had learned - that I would feel that I didn't deserve this and that God had abandoned me. Then I would usually try to fix things myself. When I would fail, I would then call upon Him, and he would bail me out, change the situation, and slowly mend all the broken parts. But this time, I felt there was no way my life could be fixed. I was broken beyond repair. I felt I had no mission, that my life had no purpose.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was so tired of starting over. For the first time in my life I felt I had some material advantage, and I did not want that to change - the children enjoyed it so much, and so did I. I chose not to pray about it - I felt I would sacrifice my happiness for the material gain of the children and I. I had messed up my life too much, too many times. There was nothing left for me. I decided I would do what my husband said, and just "deal with it." I would resign myself to ignoring the problems around me, and just struggle from day to day, with a fake smile and heavy heart. Love between people seemed only a fa&amp;ccedil;ade for control. I felt already dead; my heart knew no joy. I was without hope, and felt helplessly broken.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Although I refused to see the storm swirling under my own roof, I couldn't ignore the rain and thunderclouds gathering outside over the valley. Strong winds were blowing up the hill over the pasture. The rain was pelting the garden and sounded like marbles dropping on the metal-roofed sheds. I had to go check on the horses. I had to make sure they were safe. That's when I ran out of time. And I would never look at time, and many other things, the same way again. My old life would soon be over; the former anxiety ridden, hopeless person I was, literally died on that summer day&amp;hellip;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The last thing I remember about the strike itself was doing an uncontrollable electrical "dance" as my muscles contorted this way and that &amp;mdash; reminiscent of the wild gyrations of John Travolta in Saturday Night Fever! I felt no pain. In that split second, I turned around and tried to push my chest against the corner of the parked truck, knowing that electrical shocks often stop the heart. Then, my eyesight narrowed and I felt my body slowly slide down the bumper onto the wet earth; and all went black&amp;hellip;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next thing I knew, I found myself standing on nothing, way up in the universe, and there were distant colorful planets all around me. I could see misty pinpoints of stars through my right arm, and when I moved it back and forth it made the stars look wiggly, like a reflection on water. I felt dizzy. I had a sense of being able to see not only in front of me, but all around me at the same time. Floating just a few feet from me, I saw a man with a spirit body just like mine (no wings), though he was short and had slanted eyes. He spoke to me with a voice that I heard inside my own head, saying: "Don't be afraid, it's ok."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other side of me, another spirit person, this one much taller and with chiseled facial features (again no wings), nodded approvingly at me. All the while, we were moving with great speed toward a great ellipsed ball of spinning light; it was brilliantly white in the middle and yellowish on the outside edges. The closer we got to it, the more I felt overwhelming Love; it seemed so warm and comforting, it encompassed my very being&amp;hellip;like the security of a favorite grandfather's broad arms wrapped around a child as he crawls up onto his lap. How wonderful I felt!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We stopped. The bright light was still far from me. I wanted to go on, I felt like a magnet, irresistibly drawn. The desire to "blend" had grown stronger the closer we got &amp;mdash; I knew this place was the heavenly throne of God himself!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why had we stopped? As I stood there confused, yearning toward the Great Almighty beyond my reach, a glowing luminousness appeared in front of me. Gold and white sparkles came together in a glowing spiritual body, a giant image in the shape of a man with broad shoulders. A Divine Presence was here!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A gentle voice called out from this realm of golden sparkles massed brilliantly in front of me &amp;mdash; "What Have You Learned?" he asked, in a nondiscriminatory and non-accusing way. The voice was so soft and tender, yet the presence of Divine Authority was there; I knew that it was the voice of God's own son, the empowered Jesus Christ.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then - all of a sudden, life events unfolded before my very eyes! Key moments where I showed anger to people, and also where I had showed love, appeared like scenes out of a movie! I could feel the anger and hurt of the other person whenever I had been mean; and I also felt the anger as it rippled on through to others. I had never before faced the horrid deepness of my own sin. Then, where I showed love to people, I felt that too; and how much further that rippled out from person to person, as a warm pulse triggering cause and effect in all things that were wonderful and blessed&amp;hellip;I had never before experienced such joy!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then the presence of Christ said, "The Flesh is the Test of the Spirit&amp;hellip;Love Each Other." Words of wisdom imparted to me! I felt overwhelmed with love, and so privileged.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wanted to stay! I wanted to join myself with God's swirling life force, His Essence, His Heaven, was just beyond the presence of Jesus! But, I wasn't allowed to go any further. I wanted to go to God! I wanted to feel more Love! "Why can't I be with you now Father? Please, God, Please!"
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I listened as hard as I could listen, waiting for His Words. Then, just on the outside of my understanding, I faintly heard voices singing the most beautiful melody I had ever heard in my whole life. I knew that these were the blessed voices of angels and those joined with God, and came from His Swirling Brilliant Presence, Heaven.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I knew it was praise for The Father, but I just couldn't make out what the words were saying. I felt so sad&amp;hellip;I knew I needed to go back to the earth. I knew I had to make a "better movie." How I wanted to stay! But, there was also a knowing that I did have a choice in this, although the desire to prove my love for God was overwhelming. Yes, I wanted to stay. But, there and then, I vowed to be a vessel to do only His Will, if he could use me. I would go back.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I absolutely gave myself to him. I wanted desperately to show how much I loved him! His Will, not my own, would govern the rest of my life. If he could use this broken piece of clay from the earth, it was all his. I totally dedicated myself and surrendered all desires. Instantly, I felt a child-like sense of wonderment as a warm flood of bliss and peace overpowered me, and a warm tingling sensation filled me, like warm liquid honey flowing from the top of my head down to my very toes! What was happening to me? I did not know. Only later did I find out that this is referred to as the baptism of the Holy Spirit, an anointing more commonly experienced on earth. At that moment I knew that I would spend the rest of my earthly life showing God how much I loved him, by helping his children, whom he loved. They would be shown the true identity of a Powerful Loving God, desiring to be supernaturally active in their lives. I had a mission!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The spirit on my right then talked inside my head again, and answered many questions on my mind. He also taught me details about many wonderful and sacred things. Many of these things I am still trying to integrate and fully understand. It is almost like trying to learn another language without being given the basic alphabet for it. So, at this point, there are deeper things I have told no one, and keep only to myself. Often, when in prayer to the Father I will ask him to further my understanding on these matters, yet I get the distinct feeling that true understanding will be revealed only on a "need to know" basis. There was no need to occupy myself with them right now.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
However, for some reason a seed was planted within me; a groundwork had been laid. And I knew that if he wanted me to share this information later on, he would tell me, and give me the reasoning ability to understand it. In fact, many things "I didn't know I knew" end up being in the pages of the books he asks me to write, and what a joy they have turned out to be &amp;mdash; to love so many people in this way, and to be loved back!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While I floated there before the Christ Consciousness, the very Presence of Jesus, the spirit then told me something that  I didn't at all understand: "Welcome to the world of healers," he said. This was a shock - I had no idea what that meant. I had never believed in such a thing! I had been ordained back in 1979 in a church that believed healing had died out in the first century, and also that NDEs were chemical reactions released in the brain. What could this mean?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At this point the Christ went back into formless sparkles and faded away, and the stars and space behind his glowing features were visible once again. Such effervescent beauty and colors twinkled around me, like being in the midst of a sparkling aurora borealis! So many shapes of heavenly bodies transfixed in the cosmos, all unique and necessary, all untold distances away. Yet they felt so close that it seemed I could reach out and pluck them out of the sky, and carry them home cupped in my hands.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The slant-eyed spirit went on and continued to teach me even more. He pointed out different stars, planets, distant colorful swirling lights of all kinds, and gave names for all of them. He continued to fill me up and give me answers to thousands of questions that I never had questions for! Reams of information seemed to be exploding in my brain, like an empty library suddenly being realized! Details flooded my being about many wonderful and sacred things. I wondered: were these things newly learned, or just somehow remembered? Everything somehow felt familiar, in the Oneness of it all.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The spirit who was speaking to me did not offer his name, and I did not ask. I wanted to be careful to show homage only to the True God and Christ, not to any one else. I then felt myself sinking, as if falling through a bed. I was being pulled back.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With that, I woke up, my husband shaking me by the shoulders. Somehow my physical body was now lying on the front seat of the truck, although I had left it outside in the mud. Since I had left the house to go to the tractor shed, three hours had passed. The storm had gone, but left evidence that at least three other strikes had occurred on the pasture, besides the one that had struck me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
"Welcome to the World of Healers"
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the emergency room I was hooked up with wires and given tests to check my heart. A thorough exam revealed that it had not been damaged. But, my eyes and ears were affected very badly, as was my sense of balance. I felt dizzy, but keenly aware of the reality of my experience. The only piece of jewelry I was wearing was a single diamond earring. A brown burn mark encircled the gold stud where it went through my ear. My skin tingled all over and was extremely sensitive to the touch, especially on my arms and in my hands.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The doctors told me that I had been very lucky; the doctor said that often an arm or leg gets blown off during a strike (was he kidding?). People often die (and don't come back &amp;mdash; yes, I knew that). They reasoned that because I was holding the chain-link with one hand and the wet wooden pole with the other, the current had passed through me, instead of grounding in my body. I knew they wouldn't believe me if I told them it had been a Divine Strike, that God used this as a wake-up call, and that I had been before the Presence of God ( and oh, by the way, Jesus spoke to me!).  They would have kept me a lot longer than they did, and probably in a little white jacket, in a locked padded room to boot!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spent a few days in bed, oscillating between a wild mixture of extreme happiness and unbelievable sadness. The emotions ran deeper than any I had ever felt. I was glad for the experience, but I had wanted to stay there! I kept re-living the event over and over in my mind, every detail emblazoned into my brain. I was determined that even if I forgot my own name, I would never forget this. I tried painting what I had seen - oil paints on canvas. The colors, no matter how I mixed them, were not brilliant enough. Nothing could capture what I had seen and felt. I felt sad again. Then once more, happy for the experience. Then confused. What did it all mean?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
My First Healing Experience &amp;mdash; a Horse!
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After a few days, I was back to my chores, including putting salve on Star's skin infection. For six weeks I had smoothed on the medicine the vet had given me, but still the red blisters kept spreading and killing the hair all around his girth. Now I had run out of medicine, so I just rubbed his belly lightly around the outside of the infection because he had grown used to the attention. I noticed that my hands were getting very hot. I thought it must be bacteria from the infection, and when I washed my hands under cold water it went away. I didn't think anything of it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next day, I walked up to rub his belly again - reminding myself to get new salve soon - and noticed that all the blisters had turned white and some were falling off. I once more rubbed around the infection, and my hands turned hot once more. The next day when I went out, all the blisters had fallen off, and there was evidence of new hair growing back. I thought this was mere coincidence.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next week, I took my cat in to be spayed. The vet said it would take 10 days for the stitches to completely heal. On the first day, she didn't want anything to do with me. But, the second day, she was in my lap as much as possible. She just would not leave me alone - even yowling for me if I left the room! Every time I would rub her and pet her, I found that my hands would heat up again. On the third day, she tried pulling the stitches out with her teeth. On the morning of the fourth day, I decided to look at what was going on, and found that the skin had healed so well that the stitches were puckering her skin up tight. I found myself embarrassed to take her back to the vet - what would he say? So I carefully cut the threads and pulled them out myself, through skin that bore no surgical scar. I began to understand what was happening.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then, I wondered, will this work on humans? The very next day, I said a prayer to God, laid my hands hot on my forehead, and on various parts of my body. Then, I made an appointment with the doctor. A previous mammogram had shown lumps in my breasts. A former doctor had told me I had fibroid cysts in my uterus, which could only be removed through surgery. Also, I had a torn rotator cuff in my shoulder, which had prevented me from sleeping well for the past six months.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I anxiously awaited the test results:
&amp;hellip;the mammogram showed the lumps were all gone.
&amp;hellip;the diagnostic ultrasound showed clear, the fibroid cysts had disappeared.
&amp;hellip;also, I could sleep at night without any pain; my rotator cuff was healed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
God had blessed me with the gift of healing! This is what he had meant!
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hesitantly, I started sharing this new gift with my friends - and that's when I ran into trouble. I found that I was taking the pain of their ailment onto myself. If they had a migraine, I would get a migraine. If they had stomach pain, I would get stomach pain. That scared me - I found myself afraid to use the gift. Maybe I was using it wrong? Why would God give me a gift that would harm me to use it? I felt I wouldn't last very long in this work. And yet, I knew in my heart that God wouldn't give me something that would be unsafe for me to use. What was I missing?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I thought I might find answers if I watched the healing ministries on TV. For the first time in my life I wondered if they could actually be legitimate. I had never believed in this sort of thing - I had felt it was a fake, showy display to raise money and give people false hope. Now I wanted desperately to talk to one of them. Did they feel sick afterward? Had they each been told, "Welcome to the world of healers?" in some way? Was I part of this same group? What did God want me to understand?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I continued on this way for a time, confused by the gift. I thought maybe I would work only on animals; I did not feel their pain. I imagined myself working for a veterinarian, alone in a back room, quietly healing the animals. I didn't know what to do.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I prayed for understanding, and what I found was the Lord's words overflowing back at me. On and on the scriptures popped out of the Bible, the pages randomly falling open to pertinent information, my eyes emblazoned on the scriptures he wanted me to see. They popped out as brightly as if a yellow marker pen highlighted them!  Dozens of scriptures!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"For I know the plans I have for you," declares the Lord, "plans to prosper you and not to harm you, plans to give you hope and a future." (Jer. 29:11)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"You are the light of the world. A city on a hill cannot be hidden. Neither do people light a lamp and put it under a bowl. Instead they put it on its stand, and it gives light to everyone in the house. In the same way, let your light shine before men, that they may see your good deeds and praise your Father in heaven." (Mt. 5:14)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"...fan into flame the gift of God, which is in you through the laying on of my hands. For God did not give us a spirit of timidity, but a spirit of power, of love and of self-discipline." (2 Tim. 1:6)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Through his Word he kept reminding me that when the Lord gives his people a commission or Divine gift, he does not do it without a specific purpose. So many times I had been absolutely shattered, yet he had still held me gently in the palm of his hands. There had also been many times we had walked together hand-in-hand, and many times I had turned away from him, hid my face in shame, and withdrew my hand from his. Yet, his arm was still outstretched, and he still loved me&amp;hellip;I was astonished. Everything I had done and He Still Loved Me! Unbelievable! And now, he gave me a real purpose, along with a job where I would be working in direct communion with him everyday. He wasn't tired of me yet! I would also be making friends and helping people from all walks of life, social standing, color and religious background. I would get to be there when he went to work. I would get to see the miracles as he reached out to tell his children he is real and cares about them, manifesting reality out of the invisible.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So why the lightning strike and near-death experience? I truly feel he had gone through all this trouble to let me know my life's path. I had been so stubborn and resistant, having "blinders" on and putting "God in a box," that only an empirical, first-hand experience would open me up to my true created nature. I had a purpose now, and I did not have to suffer in silence or ignore my plight. I could be strong again, because his strength was in me. Everything was made anew! By Free Will I had died to self at the foot of heaven and upon the earth - and he had resurrected me up again. I was a new person. He opened me up! I vowed I would never allow myself to be closed down again!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I asked to be as giving as the wind, that I would go wherever he led me. "The wind blows wherever it pleases. You hear its sound, but you cannot tell where it comes from or where it is going. So it is with everyone born of the Spirit." (John 3:8)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
Reiki Healing in the God-Spot
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One day, a trusted friend invited me to a Reiki ("ray'key") Open House near my home in Nashville, Tennessee. She said there were other people with the gift there, and people were being healed. I cautiously went with her. I found people praying and laughing, and the laying-on-of hands. Their hands were hot like mine; and the people they were attending had come from the community, mostly the poor and the curious. Twice a month they would gather here in this upper room and invite any who wanted to come. I watched them, and it made me wonder. I felt comforted that there was a large painting of Jesus hanging predominately on the wall. On the desk was information about this Japanese technique, and I thumbed through it. There was a picture of a man, a Christian minister, Dr. Usui, who had given Japanese hands-on-healing this name of Reiki in the early 1800's, although it had been known for hundreds of years before. He had started many healing clinics in Japan. I looked at the picture and gasped - I knew this man!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This was the spirit with slant-eyes and rounded belly that was beside me during my near-death experience! The very same man! My Goodness! God works in very, very mysterious ways!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With this, I knew what my next step was; and I went through the training classes of Usui Reiki, eventually receiving what is called the Reiki Master Degree. The pain I had been feeling was gone. Now, I felt energized and euphoric after the healings! I was not taking upon myself the other person's pain anymore. I believe the pain was merely a catalyst to keep seeking answers, and to lead me to my next step. So, now I was using the "Gifts of the Spirit" offering "Healing Prayer" and "Divine Healing" under the title of "Reiki Practitioner." But why had God led me up this path, one that I had never heard of before? Why was this strange name added to the calling of my mission?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I have given much thought and prayer to this question. And this is what I have been given as the answer. And since he continues to use this vessel for even more powerful works, I know his blessing has been upon it. I have learned not to judge where his Spirit places my foot, that wherever I am he places an angel to protect and shield me with a flaming sword of Unconditional Love.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Reiki is recognized by the American Medical Association as a Complementary Alternative Medicine. It is used in many hospitals by trained nurses and doctors as a complement to normal health care needs. It has consistent and measurable results. There are more and more studies (including double-blind studies by NIH) and more research is being conducted. This form of hands-on-healing is easily accessible, and more and more accepted by the public. In this way, I have an opportunity to work with people of all religions and faiths, and people without faith, and God still touches them with an empirical experience. Not all Reiki practitioners use prayer with their healings, though; so the kind of healing that I am facilitated for is could be more accurately described as "Divine Healing," which is hands-on-healing combined with healing prayer. Adding prayer and recognizing Source is what makes the miracles happen.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I have found that a person does not need to be struck by lightning or have a NDE to have healing hands. There are many people who are drawn to become healers; and by asking, The Big Guy often gives this opportunity to them as a free gift, and tests them out with it to see how they respond to it. Doors will open, or close, from there. Are they working for ego, or giving the credit to the One True Healer?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, my entire life is an adventure and an aware spirit journey! I get to see cancer disappear, brain tumors shrink and go away, blind eyes see and deaf ears hear. I get to be there when the arthritis melts away and chronic disease abates. I get to be there to see the addictions leave without side-effects, and I get to help bring peace, calmness and painlessness to those transitioning in death. I meet people from all over the world, and get to be there everyday when incredible things happen, and form friendships that are deep and loving. Along the way, this wider connection with God has led to other interventions of Spirit, such as miraculous long-distance healings, medical intuitiveness, locating missing children, visions and prophecies, and even helping the FBI on 9-11. Through this Oneness Connection, nothing is impossible! I praise God continually as I enjoy every day, every moment, and every experience I have! I am always amazed how he brings his kids together, to learn to love one another and help each other. It totally humbles me to be involved in this kind of work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The point that I want you to remember from my experience is this: you don't have to be struck by lightning or have a near-death experience to open up, change your life, appreciate each other, or to have a special connection with God. Love is the key to everything. Remember, the life-review you have will be about the love you showed, or didn't show! It's all about love!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"But I tell you that men will have to give account on the Day of Judgment for every careless word they have spoken. For by your words you will be acquitted, and by your words you will be condemned." (Mt. 12:36,37)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I was before the Ultimate, I wished only to love and be responsible to him. But what he wanted was for me to be responsible and love everyone else. So, we prove our love by loving everybody else!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My brokenness led me to a mending of the very highest kind, and everything in my life has changed, in alignment to fulfilling that purpose. I feel blissful now, every night and every day, knowing I am doing exactly what I should be doing. I am blessed to be working in several locations in southern California as a full-time healer, and being flown around the world for healings and conventions. Even when I didn't know what to ask for, in my most broken of times, The Big Guy gave me my life's work. And I am happier that I have ever been before! Whatever periods of brokenness in my life I had to go through, whatever lessons I needed to learn to get to this place in my spiritual journey, I can release and be glad for! Now, I am making a better "movie" for when I come before the Presence again, and I'm sharing the gifts our Father freely gives us. I am thankful everyday that when I was stubborn and striking out, He stepped in and struck me down!  Truly, the best thing that happened in my life was almost losing it. Being dead healed my life; and now it heals others.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;




&lt;i&gt;
Tiffany Snow, D.D., M.Th. is the author of two  books and many articles,  and has appeared on radio and TV, including a TV documentary on NDEs.  She is Medical Intuitive, a Licensed CE Provider for the California Board of Registered Nursing, a Usui Reiki Master Practitioner, a lecturer and a healing facilitator.  For more information, please visit Tiffany on the web at &lt;/i&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.TIffanySnow.com"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;www.TiffanySnow.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/i&gt;

&lt;dtml-var standard_html_footer&gt;</body>
  </story>
  <story>
    <title>Into the Light</title>
    <author>Kesha L. Engel</author>
    <updated>2011-08-10T 9:10:49</updated>
    <body>&lt;dtml-var standard_html_header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February, 1974, when I was fourteen years old, I experienced some kind of overdose which nearly killed me.  I had willingly and recklessly smoked something called "angel dust."  Quite a rebel at that time of life, I was expelled from the public school system---too many truancies and disruptive behavior.  I also was recently arrested for drug use by undercover cops at the new school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The night of the overdose I entered my room and closed the door to the outside world.  I drifted into a deep, faraway sleep.  The voices from other parts of the house faded into the distance.  My body lay listless on the bed and I suddenly was some place outside of myself---beyond the storm, the suburbs and the city lights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was traveling, tumbling through the darkness into a strange void of unfamiliar space.  Sharp, stabbing nameless voices, without form, seemed to chase me in the blackness.  Loud, buzzing, irritating and incessant taunting seemed to pursue me.  It was as if I was spinning, but I had no body.  I felt confused, frightened and utterly alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I reached the peak of my despair, a new thought pierced my awareness.  A dim and promising glow appeared in the farthest reaches of space.  Intuitively, I knew that the light would save me from this torment.  It seemed to magnetize me like a beacon in a sea of darkness and I knew I had to direct myself to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The brilliance grew stronger and more alluring as my desire to be near it surged.  And in an instatn, I was completely and profoundly surrounded by the brightest, most intense and loving light imaginable.  It welcomed me with a sense of peace that I had never known before.  I was awestruck.  But I was thinking, "How did I get here?  Do I really deserve this?"&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that thought, I felt myself slide off the beam, as if all my protection vanished.  The forces of darkness were just too great.  I heard that haunting, malicious laughter again and it drew me down into an abyss.  I wondered how I could retrieve the peace.  What had I done wrong?  Was it real?  In a flash, I traversed the universe and felt enveloped in serenity once again.  This time it was as if I could see without eyes.  I perceived an ethereal mist and a lush, life-filled place awaited me.  My energy merged with that of a golden-white glowing essence---one of complete love and absolute safety.  Filled with bliss, I knew I was going home at last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet before I could cross the threshold into my true home, I also knew that I must return.  Something unspoken filled my awareness and in seconds (as if time can be measured at these levels), I was being drawn backwards.  I perceived flashes of light swirling quickly by.  They were like tiny electrodes of information that contained scenes from my life.  A vacuum-like suction swooped me directly from that safe haven and I woke to my father's face bent over me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; He was shaking me violently, saying, "Get up! Get up now!"  They had been calling me for half an hour and I hadn't moved.  "If you don't get up now, we will call the hospital and your parole officer will know that you have been using!"&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt as if I had been shot back to some kind of hell, disconnected from the light.  My dad's nostrils flared with the smoky haze of his cigarette.  He paced adamantly, "Get up," he commanded, when he saw my eyes open.  Somehow I was sentenced to live with this family and it felt so foreign to me.  Oh, what a task it was to move.  My body felt paralyzed initially, as if it were filled with lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As disconcerting as it was to return to this world, I knew what I had to do.  I dragged my sandbagged legs across the floor and reached up to tear a pot leaf poster off the bedroom wall.  My dad stood incredulous.  His mouth dropped open in disbelief, his eyes widened.  "Do you want me to get rid of this?"  he asked.  I nodded and proceeded to rip down another black light poster of Uncle Sam giving the finger.  My dad just shook his head and muttered, "Unbelievable."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could feel his heart lifting as my body grew lighter with every movement.  I turned more lights on and proceeded to clear my room of clutter, surrendering all the paraphernalia I had stashed.  I stopped using drugs that night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the support of some wonderful teachers, I became an honor roll student, and learned to meditate while still in high school.  I was introduced to the works of Dr. Elisabeth Kubler Ross and Dr. Raymond Moody, pioneers in the NDE movement.  It helped put things in a new context for me.  I am grateful for the inner experience and the continuing opportunity to explore this multidimensional world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;tt&gt;
Kesha L. Engel, BA, CMT, has over a decade of experience as a practitioner in the healing arts field.  She is certified in breathwork coaching, SHEN, (an emotional-release bodywork method), cranial-sacro therapy, and hypnosis.  Kesha is available for individual and group consultations at LIVES UNLIMITED in Madison, WI
&lt;/tt&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dtml-var standard_html_footer&gt;</body>
  </story>
</stories>
